<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>For England's information, reformation, great joy, peace, and consolation; and for her great honour, and exaltation, and for the great shame, contempt and terror of the Turk, the Pope, and the Devil, and all the workers of evil</title>
            <author>Varney, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 224 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V114B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203878</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825293</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825293</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A71198)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1877:02; 2220:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>For England's information, reformation, great joy, peace, and consolation; and for her great honour, and exaltation, and for the great shame, contempt and terror of the Turk, the Pope, and the Devil, and all the workers of evil</title>
                  <author>Varney, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 102, 105-143, [1] p., [1] leaf of plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Varney, whose name appears on S4r.</note>
                  <note>With errata at end of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29672:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29672:1"/>
            <p>FOR ENGLANDS Information, Reformation, great Joy, Peace, and Conſolation; And for her great Honour, and Exaltation, and for the great Shame, Contempt and Terror OF THE TVRK, the POPE, AND THE DEVIL, And all the WORKERS of EVIL.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>The Labour of the Righteous tendeth to Life; the Righteous is an Everlaſting Foundation, and Righteouſneſs will in time exalt a Perſon, and in due time enable him for to exalt a Nation, when it may be in a Weak and Low Condition.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29672:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29672:2"/>
            <head>FOR ENGLANDS Information, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> great things are to be done and brought about for the Glory, and the great Glory of the God of Heaven; for the Credit of his Holy Goſpel, for the great Honour and Renown of the Proteſtant Religion, for the great Exaltation of our Royal Soveraign His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> above all Heathen Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Emperors in the World; that ſo many Nations may be freed from Slavery, and throughout the whole World there may be great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity, which will be brought about in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign; but not by the Wiſdom and the Power of Mortal Men, but by the Wiſdom and the Power of the God of Heaven; but he has ſtirr'd me up for the Glory of his great Name, to have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29672:3"/>his Enemies brought to ſhame, and his Annointed, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> throughout the whole World, to great Honour, Renown, and Fame; for to make uſe of the Wiſdom, the Power; and the Strength of Men, but not to truſt to any of them. In theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, will the Righteous Flouriſh, and in his days there will be abundance of Peace; ſo that Righteouſneſs will run down like a mighty Stream, and Truth and Peace will kiſs each other: ſo that His Majeſties Royal Throne will be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Righteouſneſs, and the Workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, the Seed of Evil Doers, the Children of Diſobedience, who are Unbelieving Jews, Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Atheiſts, Wicked and Bloody Papiſts, and Rebellious Diſſenters; and Sectaries will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid and aſhamed to come into His Majeſties Royal Preſence; ſo that His Majeſties Royal Court will be the moſt Holieſt Court in the World, and theſe ſinful and divided Kingdoms, that have for a long time been vexed and perplexed with Contentions and Diviſions, will become the moſt Renowned Kingdoms under the Heavens, for U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Peace and Concord, for Piety and Vertue, for Wiſdom, Power, and Strength, for Honour, Riches, and great Glory; ſo that in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, we ſhall ſoon become the Wonder and the Glory of the World, the Crown of Kingdoms, the Deſire and the Delight of Nations, the Joy of the whole Earth, and the City of the Great
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29672:3"/>King; who can and will give us every good thing that is ſuitable and ſeaſonable, profitable, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and advantagious, for the great Honour and Exaltation of his Annointed, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of many Kingdoms; which will bring great Joy and Triumph to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and great Shame, Contempt, and Terror to the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and all the Workers of Evil; to him that believeth, all things are poſſible, though to the Eye of Senſe and Reaſon, it may ſeem very difficult; that which is above Nature will be brought about by him, that is partaker of the Divine Nature, and that without having a Sword in the Hand, or Men or Money at Command. Mans Extremity it is Gods Opportunity for to help a Perſon, a Family, a City, and a Kingdom; when that many Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men, may be at a ſtand, for to bring Order out of Confuſion, Light out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Good out of Evil, and Peace out of Trouble; then the Lord of Hoſts, who has all Power in his own Hand, and all Men and Angels at Command, knows when, how, and by whom, he pleaſeth for to make bare his Arm, though it be by a weak and an unlikely Man: for his Arm is very long, and very ſtrong; and that his Enemies will know in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, to their great ſhame and overthrow.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>portrait of Charles II</figDesc>
               <head>Carolus jj Rex</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </figure>
            </figure>
            <p>The Power of Faith, it is not in making of many words, or in taking up the Sword, that is made by Mortal Men. But the Power of Faith, it is the Power of God, making uſe of the Word of God, which is the Sword of the God of Heaven, which is ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than any Two-edged Sword made by Men: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is Piercing, even to the dividing a ſunder, of Soul and Spirit, and of the Joynts, and Marrow, and is a deſcerner of the Thoughts and Intents of the Hearts of all the Sons and Daughters of Men, that are, that have been, or ever will be in the World. This Word of God which is the Word of Life; and the Sword of the Spirit, it will Prevail, when that the Traditions, the Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Lying Wonders of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall fail: The Word of God abideth for ever, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſhall prevail, when that all Unbelieving Jews, Bruitiſh Atheiſts, Wicked and Bloody Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; and Rebellious Diſſenters, and Sectaries, that do truſt to Carnal Wiſdom, Power, and Strength; to this Party or that Party, to this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion or that Opinion; to their Eſtates or their Swords, their Hearts ſhall fail: Therefore in theſe Days of the Goſpel of Peace, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi> Let all that handle the Sword, periſh with the Sword; that do not uſe it in a right manner,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29672:18"/>and to a Right End; that do not uſe it, for the Glory of the great and Mighty God, who is a Man of War and the God of Peace; and for the Credit of his Holy Goſpel, which is the glad Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Salvation, and for the great Honour and Renown of the Proteſtant Religion, for the great Joy and Triumph of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the great Exaltation of His Majeſty of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and the great Peace and Proſperity of his Kingdoms in theſe Days of the Goſpel, which is the Day of Gods Power; and the great manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Patience, Wiſdom, and Glory. Let not any deſpiſe the day of ſmall things: For by Carnal Wiſdom, Power, and Strength, ſhall not Unbeleiving <hi>Jews,</hi> Bruitiſh <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> Wicked and Bloody <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and Rebellious <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries</hi> prevail; but againſt all theſe will the Lord of Hoſts prevail; and that when he pleaſe, and by whom he pleaſe: As it is the Prayer of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, ſo it ought to be their great care in theſe Days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> for to mind what they Sow in Weakneſs, in whom the Great and the Mighty God doth Raiſe in Power, or elſe they do but Undervalue their own Labours; and Encourage their Adverſaries: For it is not enough for the Miniſters of the Goſpel, to Preach the Word of God, in Seaſon, and out of Seaſon, but they ought to mind who hath Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved their Report; and to whom is the Arm of the Lord Revealed: For his Arm is very long, and very ſtrong; and that his Enemies will know in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29672:19"/>theſe Days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign; to their great Shame and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. The Great and the Mighty God, that gives Life to a Worm, can give Power to a Man, to make all his Enemies throughout the whole World to Tremble; And that without having a Sword in his Hand, or Men, or Money at Command.</p>
            <p>Therefore as my Heart is Ingaged for the God of Heaven, ſo it is Inraged againſt all them, that do Slight and Undervalue his Holy Word, and Queſtion his Mighty Power: By the Power of God I am what I am; and will Labour to do what I can, that his Name and Works throughout the whole World may be known to be moſt Glorious; and His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain's</hi> Royal Perſon; Crown, and Kingdoms, moſt Renowned and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous among all, and above all, Heathen and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Emperors in the World.</p>
            <p>If ever there was a time for to manifeſt the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Faith, for the great Honour and Renown of <hi>England's</hi> Royal Church and State, it is in ſuch a time when that too many do Queſtion the Truth of it; and few brings forth the Fruit of it, which is Love and Obedience to God and Man.</p>
            <p>Great is the Power of Faith, that doth inable a Mortal Man, to have Power with the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to get Power from him, and to Act with Power for him, and that in the worſt of times, and before the beſt of Men; in theſe Days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain:</hi> That among all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29672:19"/>People, in all Nations, there may be a general Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Throughout the whole World; there muſt be but one Religion; and that is the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, as it is Eſtabliſh'd in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for it is the true Religion, becauſe it doth hold forth and declare the knowledge of the true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent: without Believing in him, and willing to be Ruled by him, there is not any of the Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Men, that can be Saved.</p>
            <p>As for the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> her Children can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Learn true Religion; becauſe their Teachers are Falſe Prophets, and Deceivers: Inſtead of Conſolation, they do many times meet with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; and inſtead of Salvation, they be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to great Damnation: When the Blind Lead the Blind, they do fall into the Ditch: When the People are Ignorant, and their Teachers not Sound in the Faith, there cannot be a true Church, nor a good State: The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> will in theſe Days of the Goſpel, and in the Raign of our Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> be ſoon brought down; becauſe that they ſtand upon a Sandy Foundation, as Tradition, and Lying Wonders: And their Truſt and Conſidence it is in an Arm of Fleſh, which is Carnal Wiſdom, Power, and Strength, which has Decieved many, and will Deceive them. What ſaith the Lord, whoſe Word ſhall ſtand and prevail, when all their Wiſdom, Power, and Strength, their Pride and Glory ſhall fail: Thus ſaith the Lord, Curſed be the Man, that truſteth in Man, and maketh Fleſh his Arm;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29672:20"/>Curſed be the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>French King,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> and all thoſe that do uſe their Wiſdom, their Power, and their Strength, to hinder the Goſpel, in any Nation, that it ſhould not prevail.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews,</hi> that do ſlight the Goſpel, and deny Chriſt, cannot be Saved, but by looking up upon him, whom they have Pierced and Crucified: The Proud <hi>Turk,</hi> cannot be Saved by his <hi>Mahomet:</hi> It muſt be by the Goſpel which doth hold forth Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Lord of Life, and the King of Glory; who is ready and willing in all Nations, to ſave Sinners, that will deny their own Carnal Wiſdom, Power, and Strength; he will give them Divine Wiſdom, Power, and Strength; which will Enable them that do Injoy it, for to Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the mind of God, to do the will of God, and to Injoy the Favour of the Everliving God, which is better than Life, or all the Delights of this World: Becauſe that the Church of <hi>England</hi> has kept the Word of Gods Patience, he will keep her in the hour of Temptation, which is come to try all Nations, in theſe Days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain:</hi> Great will be the Peace, and the Proſperity of the Church of Chriſt, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World: For the Lord will Judge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong al Nations, by his Word and Spirit; and will Rebuke all them that will not ſubmit to the Goſpel of his Son, which is the only means that the Wiſdom of the Father has appointed for the Saving of loſt Man; ſo that they that have truſted
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29672:20"/>to their Wiſdom, their Power, and their Strength, will beat their Swords into Plow Shares, and their Spears into Pruining Hooks: For Nation ſhall not lift up Sword againſt Nation; neither in theſe Days of the Goſpel, ſhall they learn War any more, as they have done; but great will be the Joy and Triumph, of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Great will be the Honour and Exaltation of our Royal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain:</hi> And great will be the Peace and the Proſperity of many Kingdoms. So that in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nations will be freed from Slavery, and throughout the whole World there will be great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity: This I Declare, but not by my own Wiſdom and Power, nor by the Wiſdom and Power of any Mortal Men, but by the Wiſdom and Power of the God of Heaven, who doth all things in Heaven, and in Earth; according to the Counſel of his own Will, and that when and by whom he will; that ſo all the Glory may Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to him, and that no Fleſh ſhould Glory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
            <p>This great and mighty God, who is the Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of all Hearts, and has the command over all Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; who can ſpeak Peace, when he pleaſe, and by whom he pleaſe, to a Perſon, or to a Nation, has ſtirr'd me up to Engage with him, and has given me Wiſdom, Power, and Athority, from his Word and Spirit, for to underſtand his mind, and to make it known in due time, for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Mankind.</p>
            <p>Had any one have promiſed to give me Ten
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29672:21"/>Thouſand Pound, for to Engage in ſo Noble a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; I ſhould not have Ventured my Life, Endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered my Liberty, for to Engage in a Buſineſs of ſo High a Nature, that I have neither Preſident, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, or Encouragement, from Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men; though it tends for the great Honour, Peace, and Proſperity of them: But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an eye to the Recompence of Reward, which is the Crown of Life; that Crown which will never Ruſt, when all the Honour and Glory of this World, will be laid in the Duſt: I have Ventured my Life, Endangered my Liberty; and have Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed my ſelf to many Loſſes, Croſſes, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches; to be Blam'd, Sham'd, and Condemn'd by many Men, for Engaging with the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for to make known his mind, for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Mankind. But that God that has Encouraged me, and Aſſiſted me in well doing, will Protect me and Reward me in due time for well doing. They that can deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and overcome themſelves, for to lay out themſelves for his ſake and the Goſpel, will in this World receive a Hundred-fold of Joy, Peace, and Comfort, and in the World to come Eternal Life; which they will want, that be afraid or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to own him, and to appear for him, in the worſt of times, and before the beſt of Men: They that deny him before Men, he will them, before his Father and Holy Angels in Heaven: But they that Confeſs him here, he will them there: The time is come that the God of Heaven will not be Slighted and Mocked by the Sons of Men, as he has
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29672:21"/>been too long and too much by many of them; as by Unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> Bruitiſh <hi>Atheists,</hi> Wicked and Bloody <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and Rebellious <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers</hi> and <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>staries:</hi> But as in theſe Goſpel Days they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l not Know, Fear, Love, Serve, and Honour him, he will be Honoured upon them; in bringing of them to great Shame and Conſuſion, as many have ſound, and more will find, if that they will not Ceaſe to do Evil, and Learn to do well; but they that will Honour the God of Heaven, he has promiſed to Honour them, in this World, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it may be with Honours, Riches, and a long Liſe; but in Heaven it will be with all that have been Faithful and Fruitful, for the great Honour of God, the King and Nation, in their Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in this Life, he will Reward them in Heaven, with Glory, Immortallity, and the Crown of Life.</p>
            <p>The Eyes of the Lord are upon the Righteous, both to behold them, and to uphold them, for his Eyes run too and fro throughout the whole Earth; to ſhew himſelf ſtrong in the behalf of them, whoſe Heart is perfect towards him; to Aſſiſt them, to Counſel, Comfort, and Strengthen them, and to Defend them; and to Puniſh and Wound them that do Offend them, that do Slight and Undervalue them, that be as dear unto him, as the Apple of his Eye: They be his Peculiar Treaſure, his Crown and Glory, his Portion, and his great Reward, though the Men of this World ſees no Excellencies or Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in them, yet by them that be moſt Wiſe, they be Counted Excellent Perſons; for they be the Salt of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29672:22"/>the Earth, the Light of the World, the City on a Hill; they be Men of great Ability, and Nobility; for Nobility, they have the Creator of Heaven and of Earth, to become their Reconciled Father, his only and beloved Sons, who is the Lord of Life, and the King of Glory, their Elder Brother; the Holy Ghoſt, their Counſellor, and Comſorter; Angels their Life-Guard, the beſt of Kings and Queens, their Royal Nurſes, Miniſters their Servants, and the Devil and all Wicked Men their Slaves: Do I ſay Miniſters their Servants, are not all the Angels in Heaven, Miniſtring Spirits, ſent forth to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for them, who are and ſhall be Heirs of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: So that great is the Honour of the Sons of the Moſt High, though they be Slighted and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued in this World by the Workers of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Who can tell what great things the God of Heaven has laid up for them, whom he has provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo many to Honour and to Wait upon; ſome to Ennoble them, ſome to Counſel and Comfort them, ſome to Guard and Regard them, ſome to Provide and Nouriſh them, many to ſerve and to wait upon them.</p>
            <p>He that has given them his Son, who is the High and Mighty one, the Chiefeſt of Ten Thouſands, will he not with him freely give them all things that ſhall be moſt ſuitable and ſeaſonable, Profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Comfortable, and Advantageous for their Comfort in this Life, and their Happineſs in a better.</p>
            <p>In this World, the Wiſdom, the Power, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the Glory of the Heirs of Heaven, the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29672:22"/>Members of Chriſt; doth not well appear, becauſe that their life is hid with Chriſt; but when he ſhall appear who will appear, with his Mighty An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and in his great Glory; then what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them that know him not, and have not Obeyed his Goſpel, they will be Puniſhed with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Deſtruction, from the Preſence of this great Lord, and from the Glory of his Power: But then he will be glorified in his Saints, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired of all them that believe; for he will Change their Vile Bodies that have been upon Earth, and make them like unto his moſt Glorious Body, which is more Glorious than the Sun in the Firmament; to be for ever with him, in whoſe Preſence is fulneſs of Joy, and at whoſe Right Hand are Pleaſures for ever more in this World.</p>
            <p>A true Believer is a Man of Wonder, becauſe he has the Devil and the World under his Feet, and Chriſt in his Heart, who is the Hope of Glory and the Crown of Glory, to them that Believe in him, and make an Improvement of him: And as a true Believer is a Man of Wonder many times to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo ſometimes the God of Heaven will make him a Son of Thunder, againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and all the Workers of Evil, againſt all that do Slight and Undervalue the Word of God, and Queſtion his mighty Power. It is not Men, nor Angels, but the God of Heaven, that has made me a Wonder to my ſelf, a Terror to his Enemies, and a Crown and a Glory to all them that be Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him, to our Royal Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to the Proteſtant Religion, and to the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29672:23"/>
            <p>The God of Heaven is no Reſpecter of Perſons, he that loveth Truth, and worketh Righteouſneſs, will be Accepted, and Rewarded; but all the Workers of Iniquity will be Aſhamed, Confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>He is not a Righteous Man, that is not a Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and a Holy Man, a Wiſe and a Faithful Man, a Valourous and a Couragious Man, in his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for the great Honour of God, the King and Nation. For Men to want theſe Graces, they will be found Unacceptable to the God of all Grace, Unprofitable to them that want Grace, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable to themſelves in every State and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; but to have theſe Graces in Truth, and to produce their Fruit, will Procure and Secure Men in the Favour of the God of Heaven, and of the Wiſe and Mighty Angels in Heaven, and of all them that be faithful to the God of Heaven, to the Proteſtant Religion, and the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would Men be Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Perſons, moſt Excellent Perſons, more Precious than Gold, or the Gold of <hi>Ophir;</hi> they muſt labour to get and to keep a Sound Heart, which is the Life of the Fleſh; a Wholſom Tongue, which is a Tree of Life, and Righteous Lips, which are the Delight of Kings. He that Loveth Pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart, for the Grace of his Lips, the King will be his Friend: The Heart of the Wiſe, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Mouth, and addeth Learning to his Lips: The Wiſe in Heart ſhall be called Prudent, and the Sweetneſs of the Lips Increaſeth Learning: The
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29672:23"/>Wiſe ſhall Inherit Glory, but Shame will be the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of all them that do prefer the Pleaſures of Sin, that laſts but for a Moment, above the Gain of Godlineſs, that laſts for Ever: Godlineſs it is great Gain, and will bring Men to great Fame, that be Faithful to the God of Heaven, to his Annointed our Royal and Gracious Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to the Proteſtant Religion, and the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Fear the God of Heaven, and to Honour the King, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> it is true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is taught in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no Place, Calling or Condition, that will Honour Men, if that they be not Careful to Honour God, and our Royal King in them: For what-ever Honours and Riches that Men do get, if that they do not Honour the God of Heaven, and His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> their Honours and their Riches will prove uncertain, and their Lives will prove uncomfortable: But if that Men will do that Worthy thing, as to know when, and how, for to Honour the God of Heaven, and our Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> in this World, it will bring them to great Fame, and in Heaven with Holy Angels for ever to Remain.</p>
            <p>If there be Joy in Heaven at the Converſion of a Sinner, how much more ought there to be in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when this Sinner ſhall bring forth the Fruits of Righteouſneſs, for the Glory of the great and Mighty God, for the Credit of his Holy Goſpel, for the great Honour and Renown of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29672:24"/>the Proteſtant Religion, and for the great Exaltation of His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> which will bring great Joy and Triumph to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and great Peace and Proſperity, to many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>They that would bring great Honour to the God of Heaven, and to His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> muſt get a Sound Heart, and to get a Sound Heart, Men muſt Labour to get a Sound Faith, which is more Precious then Gold, and doth require more Wiſdom, Power, and Skill to Prove it, Improve it; and to know when, and how for to Manage it, than it is to Sway a Scepter, and to Rule a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and more Honour than it is to wear any Earthly Crown. This I declare, that no Subject whatſoever ſhould Deſire or Covet after the Growns and Scepters of Kings and Princes in this World; but if that Men will Covet after a Crown, let it be an Immortal one, which the Righteous Judge will give to all Faithful ones; for thoſe that be Faithful to the Death, he will give the Crown of Life: That Crown which will never Ruſt, when all the Glory of this World, will be laid in the Duſt.</p>
            <p>A Sound Faith is more Precious then Gold, or the Gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> becauſe it will purifie the Foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Heart; it will in time make a mean Man Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, a Poor Man Rich, a Weak Man Strong, a Sick Man Well, and a Dying Man Happy; which all the things in this World cannot do: Divine Faith, which is more Precious than Gold, it is the Gift and Power of the great and mighty God, it is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29672:24"/>not in the Power of any Mortal Men, to give it to their Neareſt and their Deareſt Friend: Parents cannot give it to their Children, nor Miniſters to their People, but the Lord gives it when he will, and to whom he will, in the uſe of thoſe Means, that he has appointed, and the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> has Ordained, and that is hearing the Word of God Preached. Divine Faith, which is more Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious then Gold, comes by Hearing, but not for Hearing: Hearing the Word of God is the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Cauſe, but our Saviour is the Original: Therefore he is worthy, for to have the Honour and the Glory of the Actings of every Mans Faith, becauſe that he is both the Author and the Finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it: And though it is not in the Power of all the Miniſters of the Goſpel in <hi>London,</hi> or in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> to beget a Spark of Faith, where it is not, yet it ought to be their great care to take notice where it is wrought; and to Countenance and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage that Perſon that has it for to bring it forth, becauſe that it is ſuch a Spark, that it will in time break forth into a Flame, for the Glory of Gods great Name; and to put the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and all the Workers of Evil, to Shame: and to bring His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> throughout the whole World, to great Honour, Renown, and Fame: And that without having a Sword in the Hand, of Men, or Money at Command; without making a Noiſe about Religion, without making of many Words, or having the Voice much heard: As Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Faith is a High and Honourable Grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29672:25"/>it is the Gift and Power of the Great and Mighty God; ſo it will Enable a Man for to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare High and Honourable Work, Pleaſant, Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and Delightſom Work, Victorious, Glorious, and Crowning Work, that will try the Wiſdom, and the Skill, the Valour, and the Courage of many Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men, what they can do, and what they will do, in theſe Days of the Goſpel, and in the Raign of our Royal Soveraign, for the great Honour and Renown of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, for the great Joy and Triumph of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the great Exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and for the great Peace, and Proſperity of many Kingdoms; that ſo many Nations may be freed from Slavery, and in the whole World, there may be great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity: Faith that is true, works by Love, and Love ſeeks not her own, but the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of many a one in Court, City, and Countrey. As the God of Heaven is a Wonder-working God, a Victorious, and a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious God; ſo Divine Faith, which is more Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than Gold, is a Wonder-working Grace, a Victorious, and a Glorious Grace: That Grace which will Enable a Man for to ſet a-work the Wiſdom, and the Power, of the God of Heaven, will Enable him to ſet a Work the Wiſdom, and the Power of Martial Men: Great are the Noble Acts Recorded in Holy Writ, that Gods Worthies have done by the Power of Faith, not by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Sword; by the Power of Faith, which is the Power of the God of Heaven: Men of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29672:25"/>have Subdued Kingdoms, wrought Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Obtained Promiſes, Stopped the Mouths of Lyons; out of Weakneſs were made Strong, have waxed Valiant in Fight, and turned many to Flight.</p>
            <p>Divine Faith, which is more Precious then Gold, will Enable a Man to be as bold as a Lion, ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then <hi>Samſon,</hi> and Wiſer than the Devil, in the overcoming of Evil, and the doing of Good, in his Generation, for the great Honour of God, the King and Nation; but the want of ſo Excellent a Jewel as Divine Faith, which is a Supporting and a Comforting Grace, will make all the Workers of Iniquity throughout the whole World to Tremble, for all their Carnal Wiſdom, Power, and Strength; it is not ſaid, that a Man ſhall Overcome the World, by his Wiſdom, Power, and Strength, but by his Faith, by Beleiving in the Son of God, and owning of him, and appearing for him. It is by Faith I ſtand, and by Faith that I do Underſtand, the Mind of the God of Heaven, what is to be done, among the Sons of Men, the Wiſeſt and the Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt among them, in theſe Days of the Goſpel, for the great Honour and Renown of the Proteſtant Religion, for the great Joy and Triumph of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the great Honour and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, of our Royal Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of many Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>To Write and to Speak the ſame thing again and again, it is needful, when it is Suitable and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, Profitable, Comfortable, and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29672:26"/>to a Perſon, a Family, a City, or a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. In theſe Days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> it will be known, who are Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and who are Sons for the Church of <hi>England;</hi> many may be Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that be a Burden and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but to be a Son for the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth Imply to ſeek the Good and Welfare of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Peace, and Settlement of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the great Joy, and Triump of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> which will bring great Honour and Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and great Peace and Proſperity to his Kingdoms. There is a Generation among the Sons of Men, that have a Name to Live, and are Dead, that be pure in their own Eyes, but yet not Cleanſed from their Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; theſe are too Wiſe for to ſay our Saviours Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Prayer, becauſe they have been ſo long Ruled by the Prince of the Air, who Rules in the Children of Diſobedience, and is Active with them in all their Treaſons: Theſe have made the Church of <hi>England</hi> Black, with Reproaches caſt upon her; but ſhe is Comely in her Graces before the God of Heaven, and in her Carriage before Wiſe and Underſtanding Men; but before them that be more Nice then Wiſe, ſhe is Deſpiſed in their Eyes. But in theſe Dayes of the Goſpel, the Lord who is moſt Wiſe, and moſt Strong, will make it appear, who be for him or againſt him, and his Annointed our Royal and Gracious Soveraign.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:29672:26"/>
            <p>The Lord whoſe Wiſdom is unſearchable, and his Power unreſiſtable; is a Wonder-working God, the Wonders that he has wrought for his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when they have been Sould and Bought, is to be Admired and Remembred by all Perſons, in all Nations. How was the <hi>Jews</hi> ſold and bought to be deſtroyed by that wicked <hi>Haman</hi> and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Courtier? But what did he get but ſhame and confuſion, for he was taken in his own Net, did fall into his own Pit, and his violent Dealings came down upon his own Pate; for he was hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the ſame Gallows that he built for faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and honourable <hi>Mordecai.</hi> What got the <hi>Spaniſh A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and the <hi>Gun-powder Traytors</hi> againſt <hi>Englands</hi> Royal <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State?</hi> Were they not aſhamed, confounded, and many deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. O that men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs, and for his wonderful works unto the children of men. How many times has the Lord of Hoſts ſaved and delivered <hi>England</hi> again and again, when that they have been ſold and bought to have been deſtroyed, by the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>French King,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spain:</hi> But the God of Heaven doth Night and Day watch over and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend this Nation, to bring the Enemies of his Goſpel to thame and deſolation, that will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and reform to the <hi>Preteſtant Religion,</hi> as it is Eſtabliſhed in the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For a long time the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>French King,</hi> and the <hi>King of Spain</hi> have kept many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in ſlavery for the Devil and their own luſt: But the time is come, that in theſe days of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29672:27"/>Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign, will their Wiſdom, their Power and Strength, their Honours and Riches, their great and high Places, be ſoon laid in the duſt; but for the great Honour and Renown of the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> for the great Joy and Triumph of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> for the great Peace and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of many Kingdoms, will His Majeſty of Great <hi>Britains</hi> Crown and Kingdoms flouriſh among all Nations, while there is a Generation: So that the God of Heaven will bleſs the Earth with great encreaſe; and among all people in all Nations there will be a Free Trade, great Joy, and a laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peace.</p>
            <p>It becomes all the Miniſters of the Goſpel, all wiſe, ſtrong, rich, and learned men, that will prove themſelves faithful to the God of Heaven, to His Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> to the <hi>Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> for to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and encourage this Noble Deſign, that Divine Wiſdom and Power has enabled me for to make known in time, for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of Mankind. Let the man be what he will, or whom he will, whom the great Great and the Mighty God doth ſtir up to engage with him, for to make known his Mind, for the great Honour and Exaltation of a Kings Perſon, and the great Peace and Proſperity of many Nations; that Man ought to be minded and regarded by the Wiſe, Godly, and the Learned: becauſe that his Work is high and honourable Work, pleaſant, proſitable and delightſom Work, and will prove
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29672:27"/>victorious, glorious and crowning Work; it will Crown the God of Heaven with much Glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of Men, and our Royal Sovereign His Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain</hi> with great Honour and Power over them, over all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes and Emperours in the world.</p>
            <p>That this may be done and well done, let all that do profeſs the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> that can pray, pray for the long life, and proſperous, and victorious Reign of our Royal Sovereign, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of Great <hi>Britain;</hi> that the Lord would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to be as Good as Great, and keep him at all times, and in all places, as the Apple of his own Eye; the Lord deliver him always out of the hands of unreaſonable, bloody and deceitful men; for all men have not Faith that do profeſs it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Let all pray that the Lord would by his wiſdom and power, eſtabliſh his Majeſties Royal Throne in Righteouſneſs; and enable his Royal Majeſty to be a Terrour to all the Workers of Evil, and a Praiſe to them that do well. Let all pray that the God of Heaven and Earth would bleſs his Boyal Majeſty with all temporal, ſpiritual and eternal Bleſſings; and when this mortal life of his ſhall be at an end, that the Lord, who is moſt great, and moſt good, would give him an everlaſting Life, and a glorious and unmortal Crown in his own Kingdom: Let all that can pray, pray that the Lord would bleſs our Royal Sovereign in all his Royal Relations; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the word would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble them to be true and fruitful Branches of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29672:28"/>moſt Royal Vine, that they may ſlouriſh in the <hi>Courts of Gods Houſe,</hi> and bring forth ſuch Fruits as will be moſt ſuitable and ſeaſonable, pleaſant, profitable and comfortable to themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Let all that can pray, pray that the Lord who is moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong, would bleſs our Royal and Gracious Sovereign with wiſe and faithful Counſellours; that the Lord would coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel them with his <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> and enable them to be the Repairers of our Breaches, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorers of our Paths to dwell in: It is the Bleſſing of the Lord that doth make rich, and it is his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that doth make weak and unlikely means ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual; but without his Bleſſing, neither Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power, Strength or Counſel, can be ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful. Let all that can pray, pray that the Lord would bleſs our Royal Sovereign with a wiſe, godly and learned Clergy; the Reverend Biſhops, and all the Miniſters of <hi>Gods holy Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments;</hi> the Lord make them more and more faithful unto him, to our Royal Sovereign <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and to the <hi>Church of England:</hi> To this end, the Lord beſtow a <hi>double portion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> upon them, and grant that they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of their <hi>Labours,</hi> the <hi>ſalvation of many Souls,</hi> which will be the Joy of <hi>Angels,</hi> and a Crown to their Miniſtry. Let all that can pray pray that in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign, his Majeſty of Great <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ain,</hi> the Lord would bleſs all people in all Mations with truth of grace, ſtrength of grace, and increaſe of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29672:28"/>grace. Let all pray that can, that the Lord would raiſe up thoſe that are fallen into the mire of <hi>Sin,</hi> and that he would be pleaſed to ſtrengthen them that do ſtand in the good old way of Piety and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, as it is taught in the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Let all pray, that in theſe days of the Goſpel, the Lord would forgive our <hi>Enemies, Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> and <hi>Slanderers,</hi> and turn their hearts: That he would be pleaſed to have <hi>mercy upon all men,</hi> that ſo his <hi>Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> may be more and more known <hi>upon earth, and his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving health among all Nations;</hi> that ſo among all people there may be a <hi>general Reformation,</hi> which will bring great Joy, Peace and Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; And to his Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> and to the <hi>Church of England</hi> great Honour and Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Let not any deſpiſe <hi>the day of ſmall things,</hi> for what I have made known <hi>in much weakneſs and many infirmities,</hi> againſt much oppoſition and contradiction, I know that the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will <hi>raiſe it with great power,</hi> for the <hi>glory of his great Name,</hi> for the <hi>credit of his holy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> for the <hi>great honour and renown of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion,</hi> for the <hi>great joy and triumph of the Church of England,</hi> the <hi>great honour and exaltation of his Majeſty of Great Britain,</hi> and the <hi>great peace and proſperity of many Kingdoms;</hi> which will be brought about in the days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign. <hi>Cryout and ſhout thou Inhabitant of</hi> Zion, thou <hi>Church of</hi> England, <hi>for great is the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>in the midſt of thee, to counſel, comfort and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29672:29"/>to ſtrengthen thee in thy troubles, and to bring thee to great honour and glory:</hi> So that all thy Enemies that have been incenſed againſt thee, will be <hi>aſhamed and confounded,</hi> if that they will not <hi>Conform</hi> and <hi>Reform</hi> to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> as it is eſtabliſhed in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> which is for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace</hi> and <hi>Concord</hi> the beſt; which would have all the Sons and the Daughters of Men to live in the fear of God, and to die in his favour; then they will not be afraid to die, nor aſham'd to live: <hi>but their laſt works and days will be beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is high and honourable work, pleaſant, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitable and delightſom work; it is victorious and crowning-work: That the God of Heaven has ſtirr'd me up for to engage with him in this day of his power, for the glory of his great Name, for the credit of his holy Goſpel, for the great honour and renown of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> for the great joy and triumph of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and the great peace and proſperity of <hi>many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſuch work, that the <hi>French King</hi> with all his Men and Money has not done, cannot do, nor knows how to do: And why, becauſe his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is Fooliſhneſs, and his Strength is Weakneſs to bring it about; his Wiſdom and his Strength will deceive him, and all that truſt to their carnal wiſdom, power and ſtrength in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign: Their wiſdom is fooliſhneſs, and their ſtrength is weakneſs, who are not careful to make themſelves
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29672:29"/>
               <hi>ſtrong in the Lord, in the Lord Jehovah,</hi> and in <hi>the power of his might.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O great is the power of Faith, that doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a mortal man to know that his wiſdom and ſtrength is in the <hi>Immortal God,</hi> and to get wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and ſtrength from him, to be uſeful and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable for him in his <hi>Generation;</hi> for the great Honour of Him and the King; and the peace and proſperity of many <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O great is the <hi>power of Faith,</hi> that doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the Sons of Men to be moſt <hi>uſeful</hi> and <hi>ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> and that in the worſt of times, and before the beſt of men. It is the <hi>power of Faith</hi> that doth inable the Sons of Men for to have power with the God of Heaven, to get power from him; and to act with Power, for the great Honour of him, and the King, and the great Peace, and Proſperity of his Kingdoms. What I have done, can do, or ſhall do, by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Faith, which is the Power of God, in this Noble Deſign, which I have made known in time, for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; I would have all Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men, give all the Glory to the God of Heaven; becauſe all Glory is due to him, both from Man and Angels: And that continually the Lord, who is moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong, knows when an I how for to make bare his <hi>Arm,</hi> and to ſend forth his <hi>Light and Truth,</hi> to ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> bruitiſh <hi>Athetſis,</hi> wicked and bloody <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and rebellious <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſontors</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> that do ſtyle and underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29672:30"/>his <hi>Word of Truth,</hi> and will not believe in the <hi>God of Truth;</hi> but do live too many of them, as if there was no God <hi>that made them,</hi> and that there is not any <hi>that can ſave them.</hi> But as the Lord, who is moſt Great and moſt Good, is able and willing <hi>to ſave unto the utmoſt all that come unto him,</hi> be their ſins <hi>never ſo great and many;</hi> ſo he will puniſh unto the uttermoſt <hi>all that will not come unto him in theſe days of the Goſpel for ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Underſtand O ye <hi>Heathen,</hi> and ye <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>believing Jews,</hi> and ye <hi>bruitiſh Atheiſts,</hi> and ye <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cked and blood-thirſty Papiſts,</hi> and ye <hi>rebellio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Diſſentors</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> when will ye learn to be wiſe, to fear, love, ſerve and to honour him, and to know him who gives unto all men their being: <hi>He that planted the ear, ſhall he not hear; he that formed the eye, ſhall he not ſee us?</hi> He knows that all things that are wrought in ſecret, will be made known in publick, for <hi>Light</hi> will diſcover <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and the Lord that made man, doth not only know all mens hearts, but all their thoughts, what they tend to, and what will be the end of them; <hi>The way of the wicked is as darkneſs, they know not at what they ſtumble; but the way of the Lord is ſtrength to the upright, becauſe he makes him his hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, his truſt, his joy and delight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let not any in theſe Goſpel-days queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be a God that made the Heavens, the Earth and the Sea, and all things that in them be; becauſe that he gives life, and breath, and being unto all the Sons of Men, and takes it away when
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29672:30"/>he pleaſe from any of them; the Lord will be known throughout the whole World to be God, by his Judgment upon the Wicked who, are his Rod, for to puniſh his Children that walk contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unto him: He that chaſtiſeth the Heathen, ſhall not he correct? Yes, he will correct them whom he loves moſt, that they may ſerve him beſt. God had only one Son without ſin, but not any with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuffering; our Saviour did learn obedience in the things he ſuffered: not as he was God, there could be no obedience deſired or required of him; but as he was man, in taking upon him our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he learned Obedience; for he took upon him <hi>the form of a ſervant, and made himſelf of no reputation,</hi> for to bring the Sons and the Daughters of Men that do believe in him, to great honour and exaltation. Our Nature, it was his great humiliation, that the Son of God ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Son of Man; it is the higheſt myſtery and the greateſt humility. But why was this done? That ſo the Sons of Men might become the Sons of God, and Children of the Moſt High: <hi>And if children, heirs of God, and joynt-heirs with Chriſt:</hi> Which priviledge, it is ſo high, that though the Angels in Heaven do continually admire it, they will never enjoy it; for our Saviour did not take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Nature of Angels, but the Seed of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham: For God ſo loved the world, that he gave his onely beloved Son, that whoſoever believed in him ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this end he obeyed his Fathers will, and for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29672:31"/>his love to the Sons of Men, he humbled himſelf to advance them; he became poor, to make them rich; he under-went his Fathers Frowns, that they might enjoy his Smiles: he became a Curſe, that they might enjoy the Bleſſing; he did wear the Crown of Thorns, that they might wear the Crown of Glory: he died a ſhameful and a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful death, that they might enjoy a happy and a bleſſed Life.</p>
            <p>And has he done ſo much for the Sons of Men, let not any of them think any thing too much to do for him; but let them all be willing to be any thing, to be nothing, ſo he may be all: Let him rule in them and over them, who can beſt counſel, and comfort, and ſtrengthen them, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, protect, and reward them: The Angels in Heaven rejoyce and praiſe God for his love to the Sons of Men, in finding out a Ranſom for them; but the fallen Angels have not any to pity them, but they be reſerved in Chains of Darkneſs to the Judgment of the Great day; And then all muſt give Account what they have done in this World, <hi>whether it be good or evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The good Angels rejoyce and proclaim <hi>Glory to God in the Higheſt, and on earth peace, good will towards men:</hi> But no Worſhip or Adoration is due to them, much leſs to pray to Saints Deceaſed. We are to praiſe God for the benefit and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort we have from Angels and good Men, and from any of his Creatures.</p>
            <p>Let all the Sons and the Daughters of Men therefore praiſe the Lord Day by Day, for Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29672:31"/>Mercies, for Left-hand, for Temporal, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and Eternal: But above all, for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the Foundation and the Fountain of them all. Let them praiſe him every Day for their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in due time, for their Redemption in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of time, and their Preſervation time after time. Let them praiſe him for the Means of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Juſtification, Sanctification, and for hopes of Glorification.</p>
            <p>In theſe Days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign, too many that have made Separation from the <hi>Church of England,</hi> have proved wandring Stars, and then blazing Stars, and at laſt falling Stars. How has many of them boaſted of <hi>Church Priviledges,</hi> of <hi>Goſpel Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> of <hi>ſtrong Aſſurance,</hi> and of <hi>great Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and of a ſudden, like a <hi>Morning-cloud,</hi> have vaniſhed away, and come to nothing: But the path of the Juſt is as the <hi>ſhining-light, that ſhineth more and more unto the perfect Day.</hi> The <hi>Church of England</hi> has her fixed and real Stars, which unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> bruitiſh <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> wicked and bloody <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and rebellious <hi>Diſſentors</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries,</hi> and know not well where they are, nor who they are; but they are known to the Moſt High, and from him they will give the greateſt and the cleareſt Light in the darkeſt Night of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and affliction that doth befall many Perſons, and many Nations.</p>
            <p>Husbandmen love to ſee and to enjoy Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fields, Fruitful Vineyards, and Fruitful Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens: And the God of Heaven loves that they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29672:32"/>that know him, and do own him, ſhould be Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Good Works; for herein is he much glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Sons and the Daughters of Men ſhould bring forth much Fruit, ſuch Fruit as is ſuitable and ſeaſonable, profitable and comfortable in their Generation, for the great honour of God, the King and Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the Apple-tree among the Trees of the Wood,</hi> ſo be they that be Fruitful among the Sons of Men: They may be black with Reproaches caſt upon them, but they be comely with good Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wrought in them.</p>
            <p>Every true Member of Chriſt is a <hi>Garden inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, a Spring ſhut up, a Fountain ſealed from the world;</hi> but it is in the World. The men of the World will condemn many that do profeſs Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for they love their own, and will not quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, contend, and ſlight one another ſo much as they that be for this Party, and that Party; for this Opinion and that Opinion, and all againſt the <hi>Church of England.</hi> It has been want of love to God and to Fellow-members, that has cauſed ſo much Strife and Contention, Sedition and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion for about Fourty years; that it has been on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Lords mercy that we have not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, nor conſumed long before now:</hi> But ſhall we ſtill provoke the Lord to anger, who is moſt Great and moſt good; will he not provoke us to anger, even to the ſhame and confuſion of our own Faces, if that we will not Conform and Reform to him, and to the Government of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Has not the <hi>Church of England</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:29672:32"/>enough from the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> to Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter withal? But muſt ſhe be ſlighted and underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued, vexed and perplexed by them that ſhould readily and willingly aſſiſt her, but not in the leaſt reſiſt her? What ever Wiſdom, Power, Courage, or any Grace any Member has received in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> they ought to prove it, and improve it, and to know when and how for to manifeſt it, for the great peace and proſperity of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and not to make a noiſe about Religion: to be the Head of this Party, or that Society, that is divided from the <hi>Church of England:</hi> This is that which makes Mutiny and Confuſion, it argues too much ſelf-ſeeking, and will prove unto many ſelf-undoing.</p>
            <p>As all the Members of the natural Body act for the good of that Body; ſo all the Members of the <hi>Church of England</hi> ought for to act for the great Honour, Peace and Proſperity of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> or elſe they be not for her, but againſt her. The mighty God, who is moſt Great and moſt Good, will plead thy Cauſe O <hi>Church of England;</hi> therefore let the <hi>Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and all the Workers of <hi>evil,</hi> combine and deſign to undermine and overthrow the <hi>Church of England,</hi> they will be deceived, confounded, and for ever aſhamed. The Lord of Hoſts hath purpoſed, and who ſhall diſannul it? And his hand is ſtretched out, and who ſhall turn it back? <hi>Is not deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the wicked, and a ſtrange puniſhment to the workers of iniquity?</hi> Therefore let not any Envy or Fret at the proſperity of the Wicked; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:29672:33"/>let them be pitied: For if that they do not bring forth good Fruit in due ſeaſon, they will ſoon be cut down like the Graſs, and wither as the green Herb: But the Salvation of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is of the Lord, he is their Strength in the time of trouble, he will help, ſave, and deliver them, becauſe they truſt in him; but the Tranſgreſſours will be deſtroyed together, the end of the Wicked is to be cut off; the Lord of Hoſts hath broken the Staff of the Wicked, and the Scepter of the Rulers: For <hi>Babylon</hi> the Glory of Kingdoms, the Beauty of the <hi>Chaldees</hi> Excellency, will be as when God overthrew <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah. How art thou fallen from Heaven, O</hi> Lucifer, <hi>Son of the Morning! How art thou cut down to the ground which didſt weaken the Nations!</hi> The Lord of Hoſts will riſe up againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> and cut off from them what he has promiſed, the <hi>Name and Remnant, and Son and Nephew, ſaith the Lord.</hi> He who ſmote the people in wrath with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Stroke; He that ruled the Nations in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, is perſecuted, and none hindreth. Then this Proverb will be taken up againſt the King of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and many will ſay, <hi>How hath the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor ceaſed, the golden City ceaſed; that made the world as a wilderneſs, and deſtroyed the Cities thereof; that opened not the houſe of his priſoners: Hell from beneath is moved for thee, to meet thee at thy coming; it ſtirreth up the dead for thee, even all the chief ones of the earth; it hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up from their thrones all the kings of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; all they ſhall ſpeak and ſay unto thee, Art
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29672:33"/>thou alſo become weak as we? Art thou become like unto us? thy pomp is brought down to the grave, and the noiſe of thy Viols: the worm is ſpread under thee, and the worms cover thee; for thou haſt ſaid in thy heart, thou wilt aſcend into heaven, thou wilt exalt thy throne above the ſtars of God, thou wouldſt aſcend above the heights of the clouds; thou wouldſt be like the most high: Yet thou ſhelt be brought down to hell, to the ſides of the pit; they that ſee thee, they ſhall narrowly look upon thee, and conſider thee, ſaying, Is this the man that made the world to tremble, that did ſhake kingdoms?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord of Hoſts, who is moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong, will puniſh the World for their Evil, and the Wicked for their Iniquities: He will cauſe the arrogancy of the proud to ceaſe, and will lay low the haughtineſs of the Terrible. And when the Lord hath performed his whoſe Work upon Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and on <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he will then puniſh the ſtout heart of the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and the glory of his high looks. Shall the Axe boaſt it ſelf againſt him that heweth therewith? Or ſhall the Saw magnifie it ſelf againſt him that ſhaketh it: As if the Rod ſhould ſhake it ſelf againſt them that lift it up: Or as if the Staff ſhould hit up it ſelf as if it were no wood. Cannot the Potter do with the Clay as he pleaſe? As the Clay is in the hands of the Potter, ſo are all men in all Nations in the hands of the Lord of Hoſts, to rule and over-rule them at his will and pleaſure: Therefore let all the Inhabitants of the World fear him, let them
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29672:34"/>tremble at his preſence; who has placed the Sand for the bound of the Sea, by a perpetual Decree, that it cannot paſs it, though the Waves thereof toſs themſelves, yet can they not prevail; though they roar, yet can they not paſs over it. And ſhall the Workers of Iniquity, the Seed of evil Doers, the Children of Diſobedience, the Enemies of the Goſpel, rage and fret, and combine and deſign to undermine and overthrow the Workers of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; thoſe that be faithful to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and to his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> but it will tend to their own ſhame and confuſion? For the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous will ſlouriſh, but Deſtruction will be to the Workers of Iniquity; though they may make a Covenant and Agreement with Death and with Hell, when the over-flowing Scourge ſhall paſs thorow, that it may not come unto them; but they will be deceived, becauſe they have made Lyes their Refuge, therefore their Covenant with Death ſhall be diſanulled, and their Agreement with Hell ſhall not ſtand: When the over-ſlowing Scourge ſhall paſs thorow, then they ſhall be trodden down by it: From the time that it goeth forth it ſhall take them, for morning by morning will it paſs over by day and by night: And it will be a vexation unto the Workers of Iniquity, the Enemies of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> only to underſtand the Report thereof. Let not any be Mockers and Scoffers, and ſay, Where is the Promiſe of his coming? leaſt their Bands be made ſtrong; for behold the Lord,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29672:34"/>who is moſt wiſe and moſt ſtrong, moſt gracious, and moſt glorious; who has been for a long time much provoked, being ſlighted and undervalued by unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> bruitiſh <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> wicked, bloody, and deceitful <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and rebellious <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentors</hi> and <hi>Sectaries:</hi> He cometh out of his place to puniſh the Inhabitants of the Earth, for their Iniquity; for though the Lord, who is moſt great, has his Throne in the higheſt Heavens, yet when he pleaſes, for his peoples eaſe, he can come into the loweſt heart; for to make the Enemies of his Goſpel throughout the whole World to ſmart: therefore Fear, and the Pit, and the Snare, are upon thee, O Inhabitant of the Earth: It ſhall come to paſs that he who ſleeth from the noiſe of the Fear, ſhall fall into the Pit, and he that cometh out of the midſt of the Pit ſhall be taken in the Snare, when he ariſeth to ſhake terribly the Earth: Therefore let all that be wiſe of heart, that would be ſecure, enter into the Rock of Ages for ſafety; let them humble themſelves for fear of the Lord, and for the glory of his moſt Excellent Majeſty; for the loſty looks of men will be humbled, and their haughtineſs bowed down; for the Lord thy God, O Church of <hi>England,</hi> will be exalted in the hearts of men, for his wonderful works and great mercy towards them: But they that have not made the Lord of Hoſts, in theſe days of the Goſpel, their ſtrong Hold and City of Refuge; what will they do in the Day of Viſitation, and in the Deſolation which ſhall come from far? To whom will they ſlee for help? And where will
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29672:35"/>they leave their Glory? Who will in ſuch a day as this is plead for <hi>Baal,</hi> for <hi>Idol-worſhip?</hi> Or, who will undertake to uphold <hi>Babylon? Babylon</hi> is fallen by Gods Decree, who doth fore-ſee how all things will be. The time is come, that <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> ſhall fall ſuddenly, and all the graven Images of her Gods, and the Idols will be utterly abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht: They that will plead for <hi>Baal,</hi> let them be put to death; if he be a God, let him plead for himſelf. What ſaith the Lord, who is the true and the ever-living God, who is to be feared and ſerved by all people in all Nations. Learn not the way of the Heathens, and be not diſmayed at the Signs of the Heavens; for the Heathens are diſmayed at them: For the Cuſtoms of bruitiſh Atheiſts and fooliſh Papiſts is vain; for one cutteth a Tree out of the Foreſt, the work of the hands of the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with the Ax; they deck it with Silver and with Gold, they faſten it with Nails and with Hammers that it move not, they are upright as the Palm-tree, but ſpeak not; they muſt needs be born becauſe they cannot go: therefore let not any be afraid of them, for they cannot do evil, neither alſo is it in them to do good; they have Mouths but they ſpeak not, Eyes have they, but they ſee not; they have Hands, but they handlenot; Feet have they, but they walk not, neither ſpeak they through their Throat: They that make them are like unto them, ſo is every one that truſteth in them. But let them that fear the true &amp; ever-living God, truſt in him, and he will be their Help and their Shield; he will encourage them in well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29672:35"/>and reward them for well doing, both in this World, and in a better: But the Workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and Seed of Evil Doers, the Children of Diſobedience are Confounded, by their Graven I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages; for their Molten Image is Falſhood, and there is no Breath in them: They are Vanity, and the Work of Errours, in the time of their Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they ſhall periſh, the Portion of <hi>Jacob</hi> is not like them, for he is the Former of all things, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> is the Rod of his Inheritance; the Lord of Hoſts is his Name. The Lord of Hoſts hath his Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel Axes and Weapons of War, whereby he can, when he pleaſes, and with whom he pleaſes in the day of his Power break in Pieces the Nations, and deſtroy Kingdoms; break in Pieces the Horſe and his Rider, and the Chariot and his Rider: The Lord has broke in Pieces both Man and Woman, both Old and Young; he has broke in Pieces both the Shepherd and his Flock, the Husbandman and his Yoke of Oxen, both Captains and Rulers, the Lord has done it and will do it: They that walk contrary unto him, that will not Labour to Know him, ſo as to Fear, Love, Serve, and to Honour him, he will walk contrary unto them, ſo as to Wound them and Confound them.</p>
            <p>Put your ſelves in Array againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> all you Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men, that be Faithſul to the God of Heaven, to his Annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our Royal and Gracious Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to the Proteſtant Religion, and to the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Put your ſelves in Array againſt her round about, all ye that bend the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29672:36"/>Bow, or handle the Sword, ſhout at her, ſpare no Arrows, for ſhe hath ſinned againſt the Lord thy God, O Church of <hi>England;</hi> who is moſt great and moſt good, moſt gracious, and moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: Shout againſt her round about, for it is the vengeance of the Lord, who is moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong; therefore take vengeance upon her: As ſhe hath done, do unto her; ſet ye up a Standard in the Land, blow the Trumpet among the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; prepare the Nations againſt her, call to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt her the Kingdoms; appoint a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain againſt her; prepare againſt her the Nations, with the Kings of the <hi>Medes,</hi> the Captains thereof, and all the Rulers thereof, and all the Land of his dominion: The Land ſhall tremble and ſorrow, for every purpoſe of the Lord thy God, O Church of <hi>England,</hi> will be performed againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> to make the Land of <hi>Babylon</hi> a Deſolation without an Inhabitant. In theſe days of the Goſpel many will ſee it and be glad, and rejoyce; the mighty men of <hi>Babylon</hi> will forbear to ſight, becauſe it is the vengeance of the Lord, the vengeance of his Temple: <hi>Babylon,</hi> which is the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath been a golden Cup, that has made all the Earth drunken, the Nations have drunken of her Wine, therefore the Nations are mad. You that do truly fear and love the true God, flee out of the midſt of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and deliver every man his Soul, that they may not be cut off in her Iniquity; for this is the time of the Lords vengeance, who will render unto her a Recompence; for her Judgment reacheth unto Heaven, and is liſted up even unto
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29672:36"/>the Skies; therefore the Lord whom thou haſt mocked and provoked with thy Images and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, have laid a Snare for thee, O <hi>Babylon,</hi> to be taken and deſtroyed, becauſe thou haſt ſtriven againſt him who is moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong; who will render unto <hi>Babylon,</hi> and to all her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, all the evil that they have done in <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in the Church of Chriſt throughout the whole World: Therefore will thy young men, O <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> fall in the Streets, all thy Men of War will be cut off in this day of the Lords power, and the moſt proud will ſtumble and fall, and not any will be able to raiſe them up. The Lord of Hoſts is againſt thee, O <hi>Babylon,</hi> O Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Day is come when Iniquity ſhall have an end: What ſaith the Lord, whoſe Word will ſtand and prevail, when the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Pride and Vain Glory will ſoon fail. Thus ſaith the Lord God, <hi>Remove the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, and take off the Crown,</hi> for the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt come down, and all that will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to uphold his Crown: Exalt him that is low, our Royal Soveraign his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> who has been a King of many Sorrows and Cares; but the time is come, that our Royal Sovereign is to be a King of more Joys and leſs Fears than any of his Majeſties Predeceſſors have enjoyed before him; and it will be well that his Majeſties Succeſſors may enjoy the like after him. As the Lord will exalt them that be low, that be meek and humble, ſo he will abaſe them that be high, who are proud and ſtubborn, that have high
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:29672:37"/>thoughts of themſelves, and low thoughts of him. Is it not the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>French King?</hi> But they will know, that the Moſt High is above them, and has the greateſt power to ſet up and to pull down when he will, and whom he will; therefore <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come heaps, a dwelling-place for Dragons, an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment and an hiſſing, without an Inhabitant. What ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> concerning the Daughter of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that ſhe is like a Threſhing-floor, it is time to threſh her, for the time of her Harveſt ſhall come, and will not tarry. The Lord will give great joy, reſt and peace unto thee, O <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and unto all thoſe Nations that do profeſs and enjoy the Proteſtant Religion; but he will diſquiet all the Inhabitants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> all that be in league or in love with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> where ever they be, or where-ever they are. A Sword is upon the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> ſaith the Lord, who is moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong, and has all power and powers in his own hand; and upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and upon her Princes, and upon her Wiſe-men: A Sword is upon the Lyars, and they ſhall dote; a Sword is upon her mighty men, and they ſhall be diſmayed: A Sword is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Horſes, and upon their Chariots, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the mingled people that are in the midſt of thee, O <hi>Babylon,</hi> and they ſhall become as Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: A Sword is upon her Treaſures, and they ſhall be robbed: A Drought is upon her Waters, and they ſhall be dried up; for it is the Land of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:29672:37"/>graven Images, and they are mad upon their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols: but the time is come, that the Lord will do Judgment upon the graven Images of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and her whole Land will be confounded, and all her ſlain ſhall fall in the midſt of her; for the Lord will puniſh <hi>Bell</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and will bring forth out of his mouth that which he hath ſwallowed up; And the Nations ſhall not ſlow together any more unto him; yea the Wall of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> ſhall fall, as God overthrew <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah,</hi> and the Neighbour Cities thereof, ſaith the Lord; ſo that no man ſhall abide there, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall any Son of man dwell therein, but the wild Beaſts of the Iſlands ſhall dwell there, and the Owls ſhall dwell therein; but it ſhall be no more inhabited for ever, neither ſhall it be dwelt in from Generation to Generation: Then the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and the Earth, and all that is therein, ſhall ſing for <hi>Babylon;</hi> for the Spoilers ſhall come unto her from the North, ſaith the Lord, who is ſlow to anger, but he is great in power; and that <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will know to her great ſhame and overthrow: Though <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould mount up to Heaven, and though ſhe ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie the height of her ſtrength; yet ſhe ſhall fall and never riſe more. Wo be to them that go down to <hi>Egppt</hi> for help, and ſtay on Horſes, and truſt in Chariots, becauſe they be many, and in Horſemen becauſe they be very ſtrong; but they look not unto the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſeek unto him who is the Lord of Hoſts, ſtrong and mighty in Battel, who can and will help and deliver them
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:29672:38"/>that truſt in him, when all outward means fail. There is no King ſaved by the multitude of an Hoſt; a mighty man is not delivered by much Strength: An Horſe is a vain thing for ſafety, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he deliver any by his great Strength. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> are Men and not God, and their Horſes Fleſh and not Spirit; therefore they that truſt unto them, when the Lord ſhall ſtretch out his Hand, and make bare his Arm, both he that helpeth ſhall fall, and he that is holpen, ſhall fall down, and they all ſhall faiſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; therefore wo be to the rebellious Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, all unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> bruitiſh <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> wicked, bloody and deceitful <hi>Papists,</hi> and all proud <hi>Diſſentors</hi> and <hi>Sectaries;</hi> that take Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, but not of the Lord, who is moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong; and that cover with a Covering, but not of his Spirit, that ſo they may add ſin to ſin. Wo unto them that be wiſe in their own Eyes, and that ſeek Deep to hide their Counſel from the Lord, before whom the Darkneſs and the Light are both alike; and yet they ſay, Who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, and who knoweth them? Underſtand O ye bruitiſh Atheiſts, and ye Fools, when will ye be wiſe? He that teacheth Man knowledge, ſhall not he know? The Lord knoweth the thoughts of Wiſe-men, that they be vanity, that all People in all Nations may know the true God, whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion it is from Sea to Sea, and from one end of the World to the other: He will proceed to do a marvellous Work and a Wonder; he that gives Underſtanding to the ſimple, doth many times
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:29672:38"/>cauſe the Wiſdom of Wiſe-men to periſh, and the Underſtanding of the Prudent to be hid. He turneth wiſe Men backward, and maketh their knowledge fooliſh; he leadeth Councellors away ſpoiled, and maketh the Judges Fools; he looſeth the Bond of Kings, and girdeth their Loins with a Girdle: He leadeth Princes away ſpoiled, and over-throweth the mighty; he removeth away the Speech of the Truſty, and taketh away the Underſtanding of the Aged: He putteth down the Mighty from their Seat, and doth many times exalt the Humble and the Meek. He giveth Power to the Faint, and to them that have no Might: He increaſeth Strength; he diſcovereth deep things out of Darkneſs, and bringeth out to Light the ſhadow of Death: He increaſeth the Nations and deſtroyeth them: He enlargeth the Nations, and ſtraiteneth them again: He taketh away the Heart of the Chief of the People of the Earth, and cauſeth them to wander many times in a Wilderneſs where there is no way: They grope in the dark without light, and he maketh them to ſtagger like a drunken man. He break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down, and it cannot be built. Again, He ſhutteth up a Man, and there can be no opening. He with holdeth the Waters, and they dry up alſo: He ſendeth them out and they overturn the Earth when he pleaſes. With him is Wiſdom and Strength; the Deceived and the Deceiver are his: If he cut off and ſhut up, or gather together, who can hinder him. He ſitteth upon the Circle of the Earth, and all the Inhabitants before him
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:29672:39"/>are as Graſhopers. He ſtretcheth out the Heavens as a Curtain, and ſpreadeth them out as a Tent to dwell in.</p>
            <p>Therefore let all the Sons and Daughters of Men learn to know, fear, love, ſerve, and to honour this great and mighty God, whoſe Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is unſearchable, whoſe Power is unreſiſtable, whoſe Goodneſs unexpreſſible, and whoſe Love is unchangeable; and according to his Power, ſo will his Anger and his Wrath be, againſt the ſeed of evil doers, and the workers of Iniquity. Who can or will ſay that there is not a God that made the World and don't govern the World? Have ye not known? Have ye not heard? Hath it not been told you from the beginning? Have ye not underſtood from the Foundations of the Earth, that the Everlaſting God, the Creator of the Ends of the Earth, fainteth not, neither is weary?</p>
            <p>There is no ſearching of his Underſtanding, even the Youth ſhall faint and be weary, and the Young men ſhall utterly fall; but they that wait upon the Lord will renew their Strength: they will mount up with Wings as Eagles, they will run and not be weary, and walk and not faint. Let who will glory in their Wiſdom, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Strength, in their Honours, Riches, great and high Places; I will glory in my Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Infirmities, and in my Inſufficiency; that I that have nothing, comparatively, and am nothing ſeemingly, yet from Gods All-ſufficiency I have Wiſdom, Power and Strength for to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:29672:39"/>his Mind, for to make it known in due time, for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Mankind, in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain:</hi> Who will riſe up for me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Evil Doers? Or who will ſtand up for me againſt the workers of Iniquity? Unleſs the Lord, who is moſt Great and moſt Good, had been my help, my Soul before now had dwelt in Silence; but the Lord of Hoſts has been with me, and is with me as a mighty terrible One.</p>
            <p>Therefore they that be incenſed againſt me for engaging with him, for the glory of his great Name, for the Credit of his Holy Goſpel, for the great Honour and Renown of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, for the great Joy and Triumph of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the great Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the great Peace and Proſperity of many Kingdoms: they will be aſhamed, if not confounded. Let all praiſe him for their Wiſdom, their Power, their Honours, their Riches, their Great and High Places: Let all praiſe him daily for their Health, their Strength, their Liberty; for their Food, their Rayment, their Habitation; and for the Peace and Proſperity of their Friends and Relations; yea, of their very Enemies: And praiſe him for all Loſſes, Croſſes and Reproaches, for they will work for the good of them that love God; for God had great love to the Sons of Men, when they were Enemies unto him.</p>
            <p>To this end the moſt Wiſe God, who is the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:29672:40"/>God of Love and Peace, has ſent and continued from Generation to Generation his Goſpel, which is the glad Tydings of Salvation: That ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of Men and the God of Heaven, there might be a great and a laſting Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
            <p>God is Love, he that dwelleth in Love dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in God, and God in him: He that loveth not his Brother whom he hath ſeen; how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen?</p>
            <p>It is Love to the God of Heaven, and to the Sons of Men, that has enabled me to deny my ſelf, to overcome my ſelf, and to lay out my ſelf in ſo noble a Deſign; as for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Mankind; as for the great Honour and Renown of the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; for the great Joy and Triumph of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for the great Exaltation of our Royal Soveraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi> and for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of many Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>They that will be willing to engage their Heart, Soul, Strength, Will and Affection, in the Service of God, he will give them Wiſdom, Power, and Strength to make them able. As the Lord doth by his own Wiſdom and Power rule, and over-rule all Nations as one Man; ſo he can with the ſame Wiſdom and Power, with one Man, when he pleaſe to make bare his Arm; for his Arm is very long and very ſtrong, and that his Enemies will know; the Turk, the Pope, and the Devil, and all the workers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:29672:40"/>to their great ſhame and overthrow; and that in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord thy God, O Church of <hi>England</hi> Reigneth, be the People never ſo Impatient, he whoſe Dominion it is from Sea to Sea, and from one end of the World to the other. Therefore let the Righteous rejoyce and be glad and ſhout for joy of heart; but all the workers of Iniquity, the ſeed of Evil Doers, the Children of Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, will be aſhamed and confounded, if that they will not Conform and Reform to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, as it is Eſtabliſht in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when the Lord, who is moſt Great and moſt Good, doth inable a Mortal Man for to underſtand his Mind, to have done what is remarkable; he will inable him to make it known in due time, that it may be recordable. Wiſe Men lay up Knowledge till a fit time; and he that hath Knowledge ſpareth his Words till a fit ſeaſon; and a Man of Underſtanding is of an excellent Spirit; that knows what, when, and how that may be done, which tends for the great Honour, Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of a King and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>How much better is it therefore to get Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom rather than Gold, and Underſtanding above choice Silver; becauſe it will give unto them that do imbrace it, an Ornament of Grace, and a Crown of Glory. How forcible are right Words, but what doth Arguing reprove, to contend for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:29672:41"/>this Opinion and that Opinion: It has been a great ſhame to the Proteſtant Religion and the Church of <hi>England.</hi> They that believe will be ſaved, but they that will not labour and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to believe in the Son of God, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Son of Man, will be aſhamed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, and at laſt deſtroyed: For there is no other remedy for Mans Recovery but by obeying the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Therefore conſider what ſo great a Prince as the Lord of Life, and the King of Glory, has done for the Sons of Men: Let all fall in love with him; for if Unbelieving Jews and Bruitiſh Atheiſts, and Wicked and Bloody Papiſts, and Rebellious Diſſentors and Sectaries, do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to love him, who is altogether lovely, their condition is ſad for the preſent, and worſe for the future; but I hope that in theſe Goſpel-days, and in the Reign of our Royal Severaign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> that Jews and Gentiles will come into one Fold; and that all People in all Nations, will know the True God, and Jeſus Chriſt, ſo as to love, ſerve, and to honour him: For the Lord has promiſed, and he will make it good; for to give unto his Son the Heathen for his Inheritance, and the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Parts of the Farth for his Poſſeſſion. And who knows but that the time is come, that in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> it is to be done: This high and honourable work, this pleaſant, profitable, and long deſired
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:29672:41"/>work, this victorious, glorious, and crowning work, that will crown the God of Heaven with much glory among the Sons of Men, and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> with great Honour and Power over them, over all Heathen Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Emperors in the World, that will not ſubmit to the Goſpel and the Proteſtant Religion, as it is taught in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> That this high and honourable work may be brought about by the Lords Annointed, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> the God of Heaven has ſtirr'd me up in time to make known his Mind, for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: Therefore let the Righteous rejoyce, all that be faithful to the God of Heaven, to his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but let the Wicked tremble, and all the workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity be aſhamed; for in his Majeſties Reign will the Righteous flouriſh, and in his days there will be abundance of Peace; ſo that Strife, Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Wars, in theſe Goſpel-days will ceaſe, and throughout the whole World among all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple there will be a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace: Therefore let the Heavens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and let the Earth be glad; let the Sea roar and the fulneſs thereof; let the Fields be joyful, and all that is therein; then ſhall all the Trees of the Wood rejoyce, for the Lord who is moſt wiſe and moſt ſtrong cometh, he cometh to judge the Earth: He will judge the World with Righteouſneſs, and the People with his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:29672:42"/>Ariſe and ſhine thou Church of <hi>England,</hi> thy Light is come, the Glory of the Lord is riſen upon thee, to bring thee to great Honour and Exaltation; and the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Man of Sin, and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to great Shame and Deſolation for her Idolatry and Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, for her Lies and Fornication, for the Blood of the Saints that ſhe has ſlain: Her time is come to be brought down with ſhame, but the Lord will have mercy upon <hi>Sion,</hi> upon his Church throughout the whole World; the time to favour her is come, ſo that great will be the Joy and Triumph of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> great will be the Exaltation of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and great will be the Peace and and Proſperity of many Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Let not any deſpiſe the day of ſmall things, for that God that ſpeaks peace to a Perſon, can inable a Perſon to make known his Mind, for the great joy, peace, and proſperity of many Nations. Return, Return, O backſliding Children therefore, and remember from whence you are fallen, and do your firſt work; for it was better with you than them: Even ſince the Diſſentors and Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, left off to be wiſe and to do good; they have been the occaſion of ſhedding too much Blood: They left off to be wiſe, when they made Separation, which has cauſed Diviſion, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, Sedition and Rebellion: They left off do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of much good, ever ſince, they have refuſed to ſay the daily Prayers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which Prayers are ſuitable and ſeaſonable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:29672:42"/>and comfortable for all Perſons in all Nations; they tend very much to inform the Ignorant, to Reform the Diſobedient, to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the Weak Chriſtian, to Reſolve the Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to Raiſe up thoſe that be fallen, and to Strengthen them that do Stand, if they be but well uſed and practiced; but theſe Prayers have been ſlighted and undervalued by them who are too much like many of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was a proud, froward, and ſtubborn Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; Children that could talk of Faith, but the Lord told them, <hi>They had not Faith; for they moved him to Jealouſie with that which is not god, they provoked him to Anger with their Vanities:</hi> But what ſaith the Lord, who has all power in his own hand, and the whole Creation at command; he told them that he would move them to Jealouſie, with thoſe which are not a People; he would provoke them to Anger with a fooliſh Nation. And has not our Contentions and Diviſions about Religion cauſed the Lord to afflict us and to ſcourge us, with a fooliſh and ignorant People, even the Papiſt? They that provoke the Lord to Anger, he will provoke them to the ſhame and confuſion of their own Faces.</p>
            <p>The Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did ſo far provoke to Anger the Lord, who is not eaſily provoked, that he did hide his Face from them, and would ſee what their end would be: And has not the Lord juſtly hid his Face from the Diſſentors and Sectaries for a long time, to ſee what their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:29672:43"/>end will be: How they will quit themſelves like Men. They can talk like Men and walk like Men, but they have acted, too many of them, like Children, Fools, and Mad-men; but their own wickedneſs will correct them, and their backſliding will reprove them: for the Backſliders in heart will be filled with their own fooliſh ways, they will lie down in ſorrow. And have not the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Sectaries, experience enough, that have made Separation from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> what it is to backſlide from the Worſhip of God, from the Word of God, from the Prayers of the Church, which tends to Edification, Reformation, and Conſolation; and from the ways of God, whoſe ways are ways of Pleaſantneſs, and all his Paths Peace; and from the Yoke of Chriſt, whoſe Yoke is eaſie and his Burden Light. And what have they got unto themſelves, but great Shame and much Confuſion? When Iſrael did caſt off the thing that was good, the Enemy did purſue them. So ſince the Diſſentors and Sectaries have caſt off the good Prayers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which are profitable and comfortable; the God of Heaven has made their Friends as Enemies to purſue them: For if a mans ways pleaſe the Lord, he will make their Enemies to be at peace with them or with him, but if they do not, God will make their Friends their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; nay, the great and good God, who is the beſt Friend, will become unto them that do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him, the worſt Enemy.</p>
            <p>They that walk contrary unto him, he will
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:29672:43"/>walk contrary unto them, and will puniſh them ſeven times more; he will heap miſchief among them, and ſpend his Arrows upon them. And who will have pity upon thee or bemoan thee? Art thou not gone backward, O Diſſentor, ſince thou haſt broken thy Covenant with the Lord, in not endeavouring to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace? And have not you broken your Covenant with Men, O Rebellious Sectaries, in taking away the Life of our late Royal and Gracious Soveraign; therefore the Lord hath framed Evil againſt you, and deviſed a Device againſt you. Unleſs that you do return every one of you from your Evil Ways, and make your Ways and your Doings good, the Lord will bring an everlaſting Reproach upon you, and a perpetual ſhame, which will not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: Nay, the Lord will make you Sick in ſmiting you, in making you deſolate, becauſe of your ſins, if you will not turn unto him, in conforming to the Government of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> But I ſhall pray for the Diſſentors and Sectaries, as the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> prayed for <hi>Simon, That they would repent of their Wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thoughts of their hearts may be forgiven them:</hi> For I am affraid that too many of them may be in the Gall of Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in the Bond of Iniquity; for not keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace: but the Lord give them true Repentance, which will take off the greateſt ſtain, and bring the Soul into the Favour of God. Again, Have not the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29672:44"/>Diſſentors and the Sectaries, by their falling from the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Have they not weakened her and grieved her? Have they not reproached and perſecuted her both with their Tongues and their Hands? Have they not encouraged and ſtrengthened the Papiſts againſt her, who are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, bloody, and deceitful men? But the Church of <hi>England,</hi> according to our Saviours Counſel, prays for her Enemies, Perſecutors, and Slanderers, that the Lord would turn their hearts and have mercy upon all Men; that the Lord would be pleaſed to give to all Nations, Unity, Peace, and Concord; that the Lord would give us all Hearts to love and dread him, and to live after his Commandments. And if this had been done, the Diſſentors and the Sectaries would not have fallen from God to diſpleaſe him, and grieve one another, as they have done; but they can condemn all but themſelves; but the God of Heaven has ſtirr'd me up for to reprove, rebuke, and to condemn them, that they may condemn themſelves, for ſlighting the Prayers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and truſting to Prayers of their own making and framing, which are too many of them, neither agreeable to the Word of God, nor made by the Spirit of God; as the Prayers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are: they be ſuitable for all Perſons, for all Times, and all Conditions; they be ſuch Prayers that the God of Heaven hath heard and anſwered, and doth hear and will anſwer them that put them up to him in a right man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:29672:44"/>and to a right end. For the hearing and reading the holy Word of God, will not profit any, unleſs they do mixt it with Faith; no more will the Prayers of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> This is the excellency of theſe Prayers, that they are not ſo plain as profitable and comfortable; for all both high and low, rich and poor, and young and old. Were they but well put in practice, they would ſoon inform and reform the World, that lies and lives in ignorance and diſobedience: From all evil and miſchief, from ſin, from the crafts and aſſaults of the Devil, from everlaſting wrath and damnation, it becomes all wiſe men to pray that the good Lord would deliver them.</p>
            <p>Never more crafts and aſſaults of the Devil, never evil more and miſchief done and committed, than by too many of them that have ſlighted, undervalued, and ſcorned theſe Prayers: From all blindneſs of heart, from pride, vain-glory, and hypocriſie; from envy, hatred, and malice, and all uncharitablneſs, it becomes all the Sons and the Daughters of Men that would be good, and do good, to pray that the good Lord would deliver them from theſe ſins: But do not theſe ſins too much abound among too many of them that have made Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Who are more ignorant and prouder than many of them? Where is there greater Hypocriſie, Envy, Hatred, and Malice, than among too many of them? But if they will not conform and reform to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:29672:45"/>of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in due time, the Lord will not onely leave them, but he will laugh at them when Diſtreſs and Anguiſh cometh upon them; as Deſolation and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Whirl-wind; then they may call upon the Lord but he will not anſwer them; they may ſeek him early and yet not find him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have ſlighted and hated knowledge, which would have men to depart from evil and to chuſe the fear of the Lord; as without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the mind cannot be good; ſo without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience the knowledge is not good, for they that do flight and undervalue the Word of God, and the Prayers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they will eat of the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their Devices; for the turning away of the ſimple will ſlay, and the proſperity of fools deſtroy them: but who ſo hearkeneth unto the Lord, and keeps in the good old way, will dwell ſafely, and be quiet from the fear of evil.</p>
            <p>From Fornication and all other deadly Sins, and from all the Deceits of the World, the Fleſh and the Devil.</p>
            <p>It becomes all that would be ſaved, to pray that the Lord would give them power againſt them, and victory over them; for the hearts of all men are deceitful, and the beſt of men are ſubject to fall into the worſt of ſins: But there is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Men that will not ſay the Prayers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but will take liberty to ſin, that Grace may abound; but from ſuch Men
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:29672:45"/>the good Lord deliver me: From Lightning and Tempeſt, from devouring Fire, from Plague, Peſtilence, and Famine, from Battle and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and from ſudden Death, the good Lord deliver all that do deſire and endeavour to fear, love, ſerve, and honour him.</p>
            <p>It becomes all wiſe and faithful Chriſtians to do what they can to prevent Judgments and to remove them, and not by Contentions and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions to haſten them, and to bring them upon us, when that they that profeſs the Goſpel of Peace, by their Pride, Envy, and Hatred, are ready to devour one another. It doth provoke the God of Heaven to ſend great and heavy Judgments to Amaze, Confound, and Conſume and Deſtroy one another. Was there ever ſuch a Plague and ſuch a Fire as was in <hi>London</hi> 1665, and 1666; I hope it will never be forgot; nor the Popiſh late Plot in 1678, againſt his Majeſties Royal Perſon, and to ruin many Thouſands in the Nation; but bleſſed and praiſed be the God of Heaven, who doth daily watch over his Majeſties Royal Perſon, and the whole Nation. Therefore let all that do profeſs the Goſpel, learn to live in Love and Peace, to be of one Mind, and to ſpeak the ſame thing; for this is the beſt way and the ſooneſt way, that the Name of God may be more and more known upon Earth, and his ſaving Health among all Nations; that ſo the People may praiſe him; yea, that all People may praiſe him with new obedience; then will the Earth bring forth great Increaſes; and among all
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:29672:46"/>Nations there will be a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace.</p>
            <p>Let all them therefore that love the Lord, be joyful in the Lord; let them ſervet he Lord with gladneſs, and come before his Preſence with a Song; for the Lord is a great God, and a great King, above all Gods. The Sea is his, and he made it, and his Hands prepared the dry Land. Therefore let all People in all Nations worſhip and fall down before the Preſence of this great Lord, Maker and Poſſeſſor of Heaven and Earth, and kneel before him, for he is the Lord our God, and we are the People of his Paſture. Therefore let us go into his Gates with Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and into his Courts with Praiſe. Let all People in all Nations be thankful unto him, and ſpeak good of his Name; for the Lord is gracious, his Mercy is everlaſting, and his Truth endureth from Generation to Generation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let all the Sons and Daughters of Men praiſe his great and glorious Name, from the riſing of the Son, to the going down of the ſame: Let every thing that hath Breath praiſe the Lord, for his Greatneſs and Goodneſs; for his Name is moſt excellent, and his Glory is above the Heavens. As this great and mighty. God ſtirr'd me up in time to make known his Mind, to prevent much Ruin to Mankind; that ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all Nations, there may be a general Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; then let all Diſſentors and Sectaries, readily and willingly, conform and reform to the Government of the Church of <hi>England;</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:29672:46"/>which will encourage many Atheiſts, Papiſts, Jews, Turks, and Infidels, to be in love with the Proteſtant Religion, as it is eſtabliſht in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Friend loveth at all times, and a Brother is born for Adverſity; and the Wounds of a Friend are better than the Kiſſes of an Enemy: God in Man, and God with Man, will bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout great and wonderful things; not onely for the great Honour and Exaltation of a Kings Perſon, but for the great Joy, Peace, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of many Nations; and that without mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many Words, or having the Voice much heard. Pleaſant words they be as a Honey-comb, ſweet to the Soul and health to the Bones. And as Ointment and Perfume doth rejoyce the Heart, ſo doth the Sweetneſs of a Mans Friend by hearty Counſel in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign his Majeſty of <hi>Great Pritain.</hi> All unbelieving Jews, bruiriſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſts, wicked and bloody Papiſts, and rebellious Diſſentors and Sectaries, will be aſhamed and confounded, that have not improved their time to know and to underſtand the great Myſtery of Godlineſs, God manifeſt in the Fleſh, who was juſtified in the Spirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles, believed on in the World by many, both Jews and Gentiles, and is received up into Glory; and there is preparing a place for them that do believe in him, and appear for him; but he will pour contempt upon all them that will not know and obey him, who is the Lord
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:29672:47"/>of Life, the King of Glory, the Prince of Peace, the Captain of Mans Salvation, the Son of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, that can and will heal all their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, and pardon all their Sins that come unto him; and well he may, becauſe he is the mighty God, the everlaſting Father, the wonderful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, the Lord of Hoſts, who is ſtrong and mighty in Battle; that can readily and eaſily, by weak and unlikely means, confound and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Enemies of his Goſpel, that do ſlight and undervalue him; be they never ſo many, be they never ſo great: But he will not break a bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax, till it bring forth Judgement unto Victory. It is not a thing of indifferency, but it is of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity, for the Sons and the Daughters of Men, the Wiſeſt, the Strongeſt, the Richeſt, and the Learned'ſt, and Pooreſt among them, for to believe in the Son of God; for whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in him, whether they be Jew or Gentile, hath everlaſting Life begun in them; but they that will not believe and obey him, will not ſee Life, but the Wrath of the ever living God abideth on them. Condemnation or Salvation, will be the lot and portion of the Sons and Daughters of Men, that ever have been, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will be in the World. O that none might miſcarry, becauſe the Lord has laid help upon one that is mighty, both able and willing to ſave unto the uttermoſt all that come unto him, and he will in no wiſe caſt out; for God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent not his Son, his beloved Son, into
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:29672:47"/>the World, that he ſhould condemn the World, but that the World through him might be ſaved. Therefore he that believeth in him is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, for he hath the witneſs in himſelf, but he that believeth not is condemned; and there is not any that can be a witneſs for him or them, but all their works and duties will be witneſſes againſt them. This made the Apoſtle St.<hi>Paul,</hi> that great and eminent Saint, count all his Righteouſneſs, Works and Learning, to be loſs and droſs in compariſon of that excellent, moſt profitable, and comfortable knowledge that he found in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The fruit of the Righteous is a tree of Liſe, and he that winneth Souls is wiſe; and they that turn many to Righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>This is a high and honourable work, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, profitable, and delightſome work, victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, glorious, and crowning work, that will crown the God of Heaven with much Glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of Men, and our Royal Soveraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> with great Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Power over them; over all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, that ſo many Nations may be freed from ſlavery, and throughout the whole World there may be great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity.</p>
            <p>It is ſad to conſider how that too many do make themſelves poor and miſerable in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the World, the Fleſh and the Devil, and that how few do readily and willingly, and cheerfully engage in the ſervice of the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:29672:48"/>whoſe ſervice is perfect freedom, and his work and reward is moſt honourable. They do well that do love their Enemies, that do often feed them and relieve them; for the Lord doth make his Son to ſhine both on the Evil and on the Good; and ſendeth Rain on the Juſt and on the Unjuſt. To do good to all Men it is commendable, but to do good to the Houſhold of Faith, it is moſt profitable, and will prove moſt comfortable. A Friend loveth at all times, but a true and a faithful Friend may be ſo much diſpleaſed, as not to manifeſt his Love at all times. <hi>Joſeph</hi> loved his Brethren when he ſtormed at them, ſpake roughly to them, put ſome of them in Priſon, and cauſed <hi>Simcon</hi> to be bound before their Eyes: But as after Storms and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts the Sun doth ſhine moſt cleareſt, ſo after great and long Trials, Troubles and Afflictions, Deliverance will be the ſweeteſt, both to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, a Family, a City, and a Kingdom. Let not any therefore deſpiſe the day of ſmall things; let not any ſlight and undervalue the ſmall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of Grace in themſelves or others; for a ſpark of Grace well proved and improved, will break forth into a flame, for the Glory of Gods great Name; and to bring a King and Kingdom to great Honour, Renown and Fame. The greateſt Tree was a Plant, and the Wiſeſt the Strongeſt, the Richeſt and moſt Learned'ſt Man was a Child. They that have truth of Grace, let them labour to grow in Grace, by improving the means of Grace which the God of Heaven has appointed,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:29672:48"/>and the Church of <hi>England</hi> has ordained; for they that do labour to grow in Grace, will have increaſe of every Grace, and ſo will grow in the favour of God and good Men, and of the Angels in Heaven: They that have truth of Grace and do improve it, will have increaſe of Grace, and will never loſe it, but will know when and how for to uſe it in the worſt of times, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beſt of Men: for the Glory of the moſt High, and the great Honour and Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Majeſty. Were there as many Nations, as many Worlds as there be Men, there is a way to ſubdue them, for the Glory of the great and mighty God, for the Credit of his Holy Goſpel, for the great Honour and Renown of the Proteſtant Religion, for the great Joy and Triumph of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the great Exaltation of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the great Joy, Peace, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of many Kingdoms; and that is by daily getting Wiſdom, Power, and Strength from him, who gives to the whole Creation a Being; which Divine Wiſdom, Power, and Strength, will inable a mortal Man to prepare high and honourable Works, to be managed by many Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men; that have their Wiſdom, their Power and Strength, their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Riches, great and high Places, from the God of Heaven. The Lord is a high and ſtrong Tower, and a Shield to all them that truſt in him. Great Deliverances giveth he unto his King, and ſheweth Mercy to his Annointed, to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:29672:49"/>
               <hi>David</hi> and to his Seed for evermore: And who dare ſay, that our Royal Soveraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> is not of the Seed of <hi>David</hi> Spiritually; the Lord who is moſt great and moſt good, has known his Soul in Adverſity, and did bring him to his Throne in great Peace and Proſperity. The King truſteth in the Lord, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore through the Mercy of the moſt High, he will not be moved, but the right Hand of the Lord will find out all his Enemies; he will find out all them that hate him; he will make them like a fiery Oven in time of his Anger; the Lord will deſtroy them in his Wrath, and the Fire will devour them; but the King our Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Strength of the Lord; yea, how greatly will he rejoyce in his Salvation; the Lord has given him his hearts deſire, and hath not denied him the requeſt of his Lips, but hath given him liberal Bleſſings, and hath ſet a Crown of pure Gold upon his Head. He asked Life of thee, and thou Lord of Life hath given it him, when he was purſued by unreaſonable, bloody, and deceitful Men; for which let all People in <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and in many other Nations, praiſe God, and be very thankful. The Lord, who has wonderfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved his Majeſties Royal Perſon, for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of many Nations, and has ſet him and ſent him as a Bleſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his People; make him glad with the light of thy Countenance. Remember him, O Lord,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:29672:49"/>with the favour of thy People, and viſit him with thy Salvation; that he may ſee the Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of thy Choſen, and rejoyce in the Joy of thy People, and glory with thine Inheritance, in thine everlaſting and moſt glorious Kingdom, when this mortal Life will be at end: The Lord preſerve him both at home and abroad, both by Land and Water; that ſo he and his through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World, may bear the greateſt ſway, while time and all things under the Sun doth paſs away: Make known in time this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Deſign, for the great Joy, Peace, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of Mankind; by <hi>John Varney,</hi> a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and a Subject to his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> but ſuch a Subject that the God of Heaven has honoured among the Sons of Men, for to engage with him, for to bring about ſuch high and honourable Work, pleaſant, profitable, and delightſome Work, victorious, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and crowning Work; for the great honour and renown of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England;</hi> which has not yet been done by all the Parliaments that have been ſince <hi>England</hi> has injoyed a King.</p>
            <p>Shall the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is the Spouſe of Chriſt, bring forth Princes, each one reſembling the Children of a King, and ſhe ſit in the Duſt, ſlighted and reproached by her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, both at home and abroad? This ought not to be, this muſt not be, but the Sons of the moſt High muſt appear for her readily, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly: and cheerfully. As our Royal Soveraign,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:29672:50"/>his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> has been the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Prince in the World for ſuffering, ſo I ſhall endeavour in theſe days of the Goſpel, by the power of Faith, which is the power of God, that he may be the greateſt King and Emperor in the World, and over the World, for Wiſdom, Power, and Strength, for Honour, Riches, and great Glory; ſo that thoſe Nations which have paid Tribute to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to their great loſs and ſhame, will be glad to pay Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for the great Honour and Renown of the Proteſtant Religion, and the great Exaltation of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> becauſe it will be for their great Joy, Freedom, and Gain: ſo that the way of the Lord will be known more and more upon Earth, and his ſaving Health among all Nations. So that the People will praiſe him, yea, all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will praiſe him with new Obedience; ſo that the Earth will bring forth great Increaſe, and among all People in all Nations there will be a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace. Let every Man continue in that honeſt, and lawful Calling, which Divine Providence has placed them in: for it is unſuitable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely for the Miniſters to follow the Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Calling, or the Tradeſman the Miniſters Work, as too many have done in theſe days of the Goſpel, to the great ſhame of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion and the Church of <hi>England.</hi> There is no Place, Calling, or Condition, that will honour Men, if that they be not careful
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:29672:50"/>to honour God and our Royal King, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> in them. And when that the God of Heaven doth indue any Man with Divine Wiſdom and Power, for to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his Mind, what may be done, and what is to be done, for the great Honour, Peace, and Proſperity of a King and Kingdom; let that Man make it known in time to that Miniſter whom God has ſet over him, and the Miniſter to the Biſhop whom God has ſet over him, and the reverend Biſhop, in due time and ſeaſon, to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, whom the God of Heaven, under him, has made, among the Sons of Men, Supream over all Perſons and Cauſes: But if that Man be not minded and regarded by the Wiſe, Godly, and the Learned, whom the moſt Wiſe God doth enable in time, for to make known his Mind, to prevent much Ruin to Mankind; then the Wiſe, Godly, and the Learned, are guilty of thoſe Troubles and Judgements that comes both upon themſelves and the Nation; and they may call and cry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the God of Heaven, to help to deliver them, but he will not regard them, becauſe he will help, ſave, and deliver them when he will, and by whom he will. Every good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Gift is from above, from the Father of Lights, in whom is no variableneſs or ſhadow of turning. Both the preparation of the Heart, and the anſwer of the Tongue, it is from the Lord. Therefore let the Man be what he will or whom he will, whom he doth indue with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:29672:51"/>Wiſdom and Power, for to underſtand his Mind, to do his Will, and to injoy his Favour in his Calling; let not that Man leave his Calling ſuddenly nor unadviſedly, but let him prove and improve his Graces in his Calling, till that Authority whom the God of Heaven has ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him commands him from it. I have been very backward and very unwilling to have my mind made known in print, and I have been much diſcouraged thereunto, but true Valour will take Incouragement from Diſcouragement. That which doth require it, and puts me upon it, to have it done, in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal and Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, it is the Glory of the great and mighty God, the Credit of his Holy Goſpel, the great Honour and Renown of the Proteſtant Religion, the great Joy and Triumph of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> the great Exaltation of our Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the great Shame, Contempt, and Terror of the Turk the Pope, and the Devil; and all the Workers of Evil; that ſo many Nations may by freed from ſlavery, and throughout the whole World there may be great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity. This is the Lords doings, who is great in Counſel and mighty in Power, whoſe Arm is very long and very ſtrong, though he doth make uſe of a weak and unlikely Man; therefore let it be marvellous in the Eyes of them that be moſt wiſe.</p>
            <p>I hope that our Royal Soveraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> will countenance, encourage,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:29672:51"/>and ſet forward this Noble Deſign, that Divine Wiſdom and Power has enabled me, for to make known in time, for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Mankind. As for the great Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Majeſties Royal Perſon, and the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of many Nations. Great has been the Trials and Troubles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> from her Enemies, both at home and abroad; ſo great will be her Joy, her Triumphs, and Victory over her Enemies, both at home and abroad: for the Lord will reſtore Health unto thee, and will heal thee of thy Wounds; therefore fear thou not, nor be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, for the Lord who is moſt Great and moſt Good, will ſave thee from afar, and thy Seed from the Land of their Captivity; and thou ſhalt be in Reſt and Quiet, and none ſhall make thee afraid; for the Lord who is moſt wiſe and moſt ſtrong is with thee, to ſave thee; though he ſhould make a full End of thoſe Nations that Worſhip Idols and Graven Images, yet will he not make a full end of thee, but he will cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect thee in Meaſure, and will not leave thee altogether unpuniſhed; therefore ſing with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſhout among the chief of the Nations; Publiſh ye Praiſe, and ſay, O Lord ſave thy People, the Remnant of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Remnant of <hi>England,</hi> the Remnant of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> after ſuch devouring Wars, a waſting Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and Conſuming Fires; for the Lord who is moſt great and moſt good, he kills, and he makes alive, he wounds and he heals, he caſts
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:29672:52"/>down and he raiſes up, a Perſon, a Family, a City and a Kingdom, when he will, and by whom he will. The Lord that ſcattered <hi>Iſrael,</hi> has ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered <hi>England,</hi> and wounded <hi>London;</hi> for is there any Evil in the City, but the Lord has done it, by inflicting of it, and permitting of it; for the Workers of Iniquity, the Seed of Evil doers, the Children of Diſobedience, are Gods Rod, and Gods Sword, to puniſh his Children when they walk contrary unto him: but as the End of the Rod is to be burnt, ſo the End of the wicked is to be cut off; they are ſuch Chaff that the Lord knows when and how to ſcatter them; and ſuch Briars and Thorns, that he can when he pleaſe, with much Eaſe conſume them. Who ever hardened themſelves againſt God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered? What got proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi> with his Six hundred choſen Chariots, and all the Chariots of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but ſudden ruine and deſtruction? What got <hi>Sizera</hi> with his Nine Hundred Chariots of Iron, but ſhameful ruine and deſtruction? For himſelf was killed by a Woman, and his Army of a ſudden routed and deſtroyed? What got <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> that proud King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> who did inſult and reproach againſt the living God, and the good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> but in one Night it pleaſed the Lord to ſend his Angel, who did deſtroy a Hundred fourſcore and five Thouſand of his Men, almoſt two Hundred Thouſand; a great Army! but yet not Power and Strength enough to withſtand one Angel. And when the proud King departed and came to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> as he
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:29672:52"/>was worſhiping his Idol-God, he was killed by two of his Sons: they that ſhould have been his beſt Friends, were his worſt Enemies. What got Ambitious and Proud <hi>Haman,</hi> who plotted and contrived the deſtruction of many Thouſands of the <hi>Jews,</hi> but the ruine of himſelf and all his Poſterity; for both he and his Ten Sons were Hanged for ſuch Treachery: But yet the workers of Iniquity, the Seed of Evil doers, the Children of Diſobedience, are not afraid nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to combine and deſign to deſtroy the Righteous, although the Righteous Lord, who is moſt Wiſe and moſt ſtrong, doth defend them, and will Wound and Conſume them that do offend them. What ſays our Saviour, who is the Lord of Life and the King of Glory? It were better that a Milſtone were Hanged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Neck of unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> Bruitiſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſts, wicked, bloody, and deceitful <hi>Papists,</hi> and rebellious Diſſentors and Sectaries, than to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the leaſt Member that doth believe in him; becauſe they be as dear unto him as the Apple of his Eye: they are his purchaſed, ranſomed, and redeemed ones, they are his choſen and beloved ones: They are the travel of his Soul, and for them he has prepared both a Kingdom and a Crown, which is immortal and unchangeable; but there is not any of the Sons and the Daughters of Men that can merit or purchaſe it, in what they can do or ſuffer; therefore ſay unto the righteous, be what they will, where they will, and whom they will, that it will be well with them.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:29672:53"/>It will be well with them here in their worſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and under their greateſt Tryals, Troubles, and Afflictions, but it will be better with them hereafter, for Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor the Heart of Man is not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, what God has laid up for them that love him; but wo unto the Wicked, unto all the workers of Iniquity becauſe it will go ill with them, they will have the fruit of their own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, of their own works, and not the fruit of Chriſts merits and purchaſe, becauſe they do ſlight and undervalue him, and will not be ruled by him, who is the wiſeſt Counſellor, the beſt Comforter, and the greateſt Suporter; who is a preſent help in time of trouble: But the Wicked the Seed of Evil doers, the Children of Diſobedience, the Workers of Iniquity, the Enemies of the Goſpel; do many times fall into trouble, and their Friends leave them, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil hates them, and God forſakes them; but whoſoever they be that hearkeneth unto the Lord ſo as to abey him, will dwell ſafely, and be quiet from the fear of Evil: much more from the luſt of Evil: but for the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Iniquity, the Seed of Evil doers the Children of Diſobedience, though Hand joyn in Hand, they will not be unpuniſhed; but many times Tranſgreſſors, and the Workers of Iniquity are deſtroyed together. What got the <hi>Spaniſh Armado,</hi> whom the <hi>Pope</hi> called the <hi>Invincible Armado,</hi> preſuming no power could with-ſtand them, much leſs overcome them? But
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:29672:53"/>it pleaſed the Lord, who is moſt great and moſt good, to help his Hand-maid, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queen of <hi>England</hi> (of Bleſſed Memory) that they was ſo, in giving her a Victorious and a Glorious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt barer'd and ſcater'd, ſo defaced and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced, that they will never recover while they be a Nation. And that Men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs, and for his wonderful works unto the Children of Men; when that the Enemies of the Goſpel do what they can to deſtroy them: But though they ſhould dig as deep as Hell, from the Eye of Men, yet the Eye of God doth alwaies ſee them. What got the bloody <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the Gun-powder Traytors by combining and deſigning to undermine and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, with one blow, Religion, Laws, and Liberty, Nobility, and Gentry. Yea all the Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily? But it pleaſed the Lord, whoſe Wiſdom is unſearchable, to help the King; to underſtand the Traytors Treaſon, and to give that Wiſdom to his Majeſties Royal Grand-Father; King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> of famous Memory, that his Friends did Admire him, and his Enemies was Confounded by him; for he ſoon apprehended the Plot, and gave ſpeedy order for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering and ſecuring of the Traytors, which was ſoon done, and they brought to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſhame and ruine; for they were taken in their own Nets, did fall into their own Pits, and there violent Dealings came down upon their own Pates. The Lord who is moſt wiſe and moſt ſtrong, will not caſt away a perfect Man,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:29672:54"/>neither will he help the Evil doers, but Evil doers will he cut off; but they that wait upon the Lord will inherit the Earth. In theſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel days, and in the Reign of our Royal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> great will be the Peace of the Church of Chriſt, through the whole world; but eſpecially in <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> therefore many will come and Sing in the Right of <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſhall flow together to the goodneſs of the Lord, for Wheat and for Wine, and for Oil, and for the Young of the Flock and of the Herd; and their Soul ſhall be as a Water'd Garden, and they ſhall not Sorrow any more at all as they have done; then will the <hi>Virgin</hi> rejoyce in the Dance, both Young Men and Old together; for the Lord will turn their Mourning into Joy, and will Comfort them, and will make them Rejoyce from their ſorrow; and it will come to paſs, that like as the Lord hath Watched o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his People, to pluck up, and to break down, and to throw down, and to deſtroy, and to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict; ſo will he Watch over them, to Build and to Plant; and he will gather them out of all Countries whither he hath driven them in his Anger, in his Fury, and in great Wrath; and the Lord will bring them again unto his Holy Place: to worſhip him in a right Manner And he will cauſe them to dwell ſafely, and he will be their God, and they ſhall be his People; and the Lord will give them one heart and one way, that they may fear, love, and ſerve him;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:29672:54"/>for ever, for the good of themſelves and of their Children after them: And becauſe the Sons and the Daughters of Men do too often forget to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their Creator, Redeemer, and Preſerver, he will make an Everlaſting Covenant with them, that he will not turn away from them to do them good, but he will put his fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from him; yea the Lord will rejoyce over them to do them good, and will plant them in his Land with his whole heart, and with his whole ſoul aſſuredly. For as the Lord who is moſt wiſe and moſt ſtrong, has brought great evil upon his people for their rebellion, ſo will he bring upon them all the good that he has promiſed, that ſo they may be humbled and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; for the goodneſs of God ſhould lead men to repentance, but not unto diſobedience: He that knows his Maſters will, and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes. All men under the Heavens are bound to know their Creator, ſo as to fear him; but there be many of the Sons and the Daughters of Men, that will labour to know him, ſo as to love, ſerve, and to honour him; which will prove moſt comfortable to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and moſt profitable to others. Let the man be what he will, or whom he will, in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> in whom the Lord of Hoſts doth ariſe, his Enemies ſhall be ſcattered, and they that hate him ſhall flee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, as Wax melteth before the ſire, ſo will all the workers of iniquity at the preſence of the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:29672:55"/>Lord; but the Righteous ſhall be glad and rejoyce for a long time: The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the proud <hi>French King,</hi> has endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to undermine and overthrow the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion,</hi> His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the <hi>Church of England;</hi> but the time is come, that they are to know, that they are to be brought very low, if that they will not Conform and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> to the <hi>Nine and thirty Doctrines of the Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no man worthy to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>England. Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> that doth or ſhould oppoſe, gain-ſay, or preach againſt any of the <hi>Nine and thirty Doctrines of the Church of England:</hi> The Enemies againſt the <hi>Church of England</hi> are many both at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, but I ſhall endeavour by the <hi>power of Faith,</hi> which is the <hi>power of God,</hi> for to do what I can to over-throw them as one man, and to ſet a-work they that have power in their hand, that they may be ſubdu'd both by Sea and Land; that ſo the people may know the true and the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent: then will the Earth bring forth great increaſe, and among all people in all Nations, there will be a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace. The Lord who is moſt Great, and moſt Good, knows when, how, and by whom he pleaſes, for to ſpeak peace to a Perſon, a Family, a City, and a Kingdom, and when he ſpeaks peace to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to any of his Saints, let them not turn again to Folly, but let them renew their Obedience,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:29672:55"/>and double their Diligence: The Lord will ſatiate the Soul of the Prieſts, of his Miniſters, with Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the people with his Goodneſs; ſurely his Salvation is nigh them that fear him, that Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry may dwell in our Land. Mercy and Truth are met together, Righteouſneſs and Peace have kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed each other: Truth ſhall ſpring out of the Earth, Righteouſneſs ſhall look down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yea the Lord will give that which is good; ſo that our Land will yield her Increaſe: Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs will go before him, and ſet us in the way of his Steps. The Lord who is moſt Great and moſt Good, will be known by his Judgments and his Mercies, for he is a God that <hi>judgeth the earth;</hi> for the Lord is a God of knowledge, and by him all mens Thoughts and Actions are weighed.</p>
            <p>That our Royal Soveraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> may be willing to countenance, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and ſet forward this Noble Deſign, that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom and Power has enabled me to make known in time, for the Glory of his Great Name, and to have his Enemies brought to ſhame: His Royal Majeſty will find that many Princes and Nations will aſſiſt him; and that, which is more than all them, the God of Heaven, who has all Power in his own hand, and the whole Creation at Command, will in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, make bare his Arm, and manifeſt his Wiſdom, Power, and Strength, to bring down the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>French King,</hi> and the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that ſo many Nations may be freed from ſlavery, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:29672:56"/>throughout the whole World there may be great joy, peace and proſperity. Sing unto the Lord thy God, O Church of <hi>England,</hi> for he hath done excellent things; this is known in all the Earth, for among the Gods there is none like unto him, there is not one that can do as he has done: Say to them therefore that are of a fearful Heart, be ſtrong, fear not, for the True and the Everlaſting God, will come with ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance and rebukes upon his Enemies; but with great recompence and rewards, will he come and ſave, and deliver his People, that wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and put their truſt and confidence in him; therefore cry out and Shout thou Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant of <hi>Sion,</hi> thou Church of <hi>England,</hi> for great is the Holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the midſt of thee, for to bring thee to great honour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown and fame, and thy Enemies to great ſhame.</p>
            <p>Behold the Whirl-wind of the Lord goeth forth with fury, a continuing Whirl-wind; it will fall with pain upon the Head of the Wicked; the fierce anger of the Lord will not return, until he hath performed the intents of his Heart, in theſe latter daies; many will ſee it, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it, thy God, O Church of <hi>England,</hi> is my God, thy cauſe is my cauſe, thy troubles have been my greateſt trouble, and thy Enemies are my worſt Enemies I have laid to Heart more the troubles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> than the Death of a Wife and ſeven Children; I have laid them
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:29672:56"/>more to Heart than all the tryals, troubles, loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, croſſes and reproaches, that I have met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al from my Youth, to this preſent time: I have laid them ſo to Heart, that many will be made to ſmart, that have endeavoured to undermine and to overthrow the Proteſtant Religion, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I have laid them ſo to Heart, that many will be made to ſmart, that will not conform and reform to the Proteſtant Religion, as it is eſtabliſht in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> When the Lyon Roars, all the Beaſts of the Field trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Lord has not been much minded, nor regarded, by his Judgements of Plague, Fire and Sword; but he will be minded and regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a ſtill Voice, by inabling of me for to make known his mind, for the terror of Evil doers; the Voice of the Lord is powerful, the Voice of the Lord is full of Majeſty; the Voice of the Lord breaketh the <hi>Cedars;</hi> yea the Lord breaketh the <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Lebanon:</hi> The Lord thy God, O Church of <hi>England,</hi> who is moſt great and moſt good, will be known to be the True and Everlaſting God among the Sons of men; for by terrible things in Righteouſneſs, will he anſwer them. For a long time the Lord has hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den his peace, he has been ſtill, and refrained himſelf, but now will he cry like a Travelling Woman; he will deſtroy and devour at once, and that without making of many words, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Voice much heard: The time is come that in theſe Goſpel days; and in the Reign
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:29672:57"/>of our Royal Soveraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> that the Lord of Hoſts will go forth as a mighty Man: he will ſtir up jealouſie like a Man of war; he will cry, yea Roar; but he will prevail againſt his Enemies, as the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the Devil; and all the Workers of Evil. Who knoweth the power of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? according to his fear, ſo is his wrath; for he is terrible out of his Holy places; therefore tremble thou Earth at the preſence of the Lord, at the preſence of the God of <hi>Jacob:</hi> tremble therefore all you Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Emperors in the World, that do ſlight and undervalue the Word of God, and queſtion his mighty power; tremble therefore all you unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> Bruitiſh <hi>Atheists,</hi> wicked and bloody <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and rebellious Diſſentors and Sectaries, that have not made the Word of God your Rule, nor his Spirit your Guide, nor his Glory your Aim. Tremble therefore all you Earthly and Carnal-minded Men, you Self-ſekers and Men-pleaſers, Lovers of your ſelves more than Lovers of God, your King and Countrey. Tremble all you that have a Name to live, and are dead; that have called your ſelves Saints, but have acted like Devils Incarnate againſt the God of Heaven, the Proteſtant Religion, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England:</hi> but let the Righteous be glad, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce all ye that do truly fear God and Honour the <hi>King;</hi> and are faithful to the Proteſtant Religion. This Noble Deſign, that Divine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:29672:57"/>and power, has enabled me to make known in time, it will be as a hand-writing upon the wall againſt all the Enemies of the Goſpel, both great and ſmall; ſo that many will fall in love with the Proteſtant Religion, and will be ready and willing to ſerve, and to honour his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> both at home and abroad.</p>
            <p>Light is ſowen for the Righteous, and Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the upright in Heart, ye that love the Lord, hate Evil; for he preſerveth the Souls of his Saints, he delivereth them many a time out of the Hands of unreaſonable, bloody, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful men, that lie in wait for to deſtroy them: Therefore rejoyce in the Lord ye Righteous, and give thanks at the remembrance of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for the Lord who is moſt good, is moſt great, therefore is greatly to be praiſed, and to be feared above all Gods; therefore let all wiſe, ſtrong, rich, and learned Men, declare his Glory among the Heathens, and his wonders among all People; for honour and Majeſty are before him, ſtrength and beauty is in his Sanctuary; therefore let all People in all Nations learn to know the true and the everlaſting God, and to worſhip him as they do in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with Reverence and with a holy Fear: They that fear the Lord, who is moſt great, will love him becauſe he is moſt good; and they that love him, will delight in him; and he will give them the deſires of their Hearts, and that is truth of Grace, ſtrength of Grace, and increaſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:29672:58"/>of Grace. It is commendable, and will prove very profitable and comfortable to the Sons and Daughters of Men, for to delight in the Word of God; ſo that it may richly in them dwell; then their ſleep will be ſweet, and they will have great Joy, Reſt and Peace, that Peace which paſſeth the underſtanding of Men and Angels, to declare what it is; it is the Peace of God, which is better felt then expreſt: that peace which the World cannot give, nor take away. They that do injoy much of God, muſt lay out themſelves much for him, in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> That Man which will make his graces to appear for the great honour of God, the King, and Nation; He muſt charge to the Front and to the Rear, he muſt charge and charge again, and that with might and main, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and all the Workers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, to ſhame; and that without making a noiſe about <hi>Religion,</hi> for this <hi>Party,</hi> or for that <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> without making of many words, or having the Voyce much heard; without having a Sword in the hand. A <hi>Chriſtian Souldier</hi> that is enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in <hi>holy War,</hi> againſt the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> muſt quit himſelf like a man; and when he has done all, for to ſtand by the <hi>power of Faith,</hi> which is the <hi>power of God</hi> in man, the <hi>power of God</hi> for man, and the <hi>power of God</hi> with man. Who knows what is in the Womb of a Day, or in the Heart of a man? Not any but
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:29672:58"/>the God of Heaven, who can when he will, and by whom he will, bring Order out of Confuſion, Light out of Darkneſs, Good out of Evil, and Peace out of Trouble; for the great Honour and Exaltation of a Kings Perſon, and the great Peace and Proſperity of many Nations: As the higheſt Member under the God of Heaven, doth give Protection for the Safety of the meaneſt Member in the <hi>Church of England;</hi> ſo ſometimes the meaneſt Member with the God of Heaven, may give Direction for the great Honour, Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and Conſolation of the Higheſt in the days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain:</hi> Curſed be that Man that dare lift up his hand againſt the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> by <hi>Sea</hi> or by <hi>Land,</hi> againſt the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> whom the <hi>Moſt High</hi> hath made Great in Place, and Inriched with his Grace: Is it not the Prayer of the <hi>Church of England</hi> for <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain,</hi> that the <hi>Lord would hear him in the day of trouble,</hi> and <hi>ſend him help from the Sanctuary,</hi> and <hi>ſtrengthen him out of Sion:</hi> For his Majeſty can have no ſuch Help as from the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> nor no ſuch Strength as out of <hi>Sion:</hi> The God of Heaven has promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, whoſe Promiſes are all <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen</hi> in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> That the <hi>Deliverer ſhall come out of</hi> Sion, <hi>which ſhall turn away ungodlineſs from</hi> Jacob: But <hi>Sion,</hi> which is <hi>the Church of Chriſt,</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World, and <hi>the Church of Chriſt</hi> in <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> muſt not look for the Deliverer of <hi>Sion</hi> to come in greater
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:29672:59"/>Pomp than the Saviour of <hi>Sion</hi> came: but he that ſhall come, whom the God of Heaven will ſend, will come, and will not tarry; for the Tree will be known by his Fruit: for he will purifie the Sons of <hi>Levy,</hi> and purge them as Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that they may offer unto the true and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living God, who is moſt Great and moſt Good, an Offering in Righteouſneſs, which will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and exceptable to him: The Stone which the Builders refuſed, is it not become the Head-ſtone of the Corner? This is the Lords Doings, who is Great in Counſel and Mighty in Power, therefore let it be marvellous in the Eyes of them that be moſt wiſe. And let not any deſpiſe the Day of ſmall things; for as the Lord of Hoſts is above all, ſo he is more than all, and can be with all, in all, for all, or againſt all, when and by whom he pleaſe: for as his Wiſdom is unſearchable, ſo his Power it is unreſiſtable, though the Inſtrument he may uſe among wiſe, ſtrong, rich, and learned men, may be mean and contemptible. But ever ſince that I have been precious in the Eyes of the moſt great and glorious God, I have been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable; therefore I have not coveted after Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver or Gold, Houſes or Lands, Offices or great Places; but I have laboured and coveted to get and to keep, to prove and to improve, Rich Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſo my Fruit may be better than Gold, and may do more good for the Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> for the great Exaltation of <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain,</hi> and the great Peace and Proſperity of many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:29672:59"/>than an Army of Men, or thouſands, or ten thouſands of Gold or Silver has done: I have no grace but what I have received; ſo I have none to be proud of; I have not received any, but what I have laboured to improve; ſo I have not any to be prodigal with: the leaſt grace which I have received from the God of all grace, I do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it above all the Honours and Riches in the World; becauſe that true Grace it is abiding, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying, laſting, and everlaſting: but for the Honours, the Riches and Pleaſures of this World, they be ſhort, they be not abiding, ſatisfying, nor long-laſting: therefore they that would have Grace, which is Heavenly Treaſure, to thrive in their Soul, they muſt value and eſteem it above Silver and Gold. To be made Partaker of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, it is high Honour and great Favour. <hi>The Righteous ſhall be glad in the Lord, becauſe they truſt in him; and all the upright in heart will glory.</hi> Salvation comes not from the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, nor from the Hills; not from wiſe, ſtrong, rich, and learned men, but from the Lord, who made the Earth and the Heavens, and that when and by whom he will; that all the Glory may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to him: for his right Hand and holy Arm hath the preheminence over all perſons in all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Let them ſhout for joy and be glad that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour my Righteous Cauſe; yea let them ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, Let the Lord be magnified, which hath pleaſure in the Proſperity of his Servants; and my Tongue ſhall ſpeak of his Righteouſneſs, and of his Praiſe all the day long; for he hath done
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:29672:60"/>marvellous things. All the Ends of the Earth that have not ſeen, will ſee the Salvation of God: He maketh Wars to ceaſe unto the End of the Earth. He breaketh the Bow and cutteth the Spear aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and burneth the Chariots in the fire when he pleaſeth, and by whom he pleaſe, in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain.</hi> They that truſt to their Chariots and Horſes will fail, but they that truſt in the <hi>Lord Jehovah,</hi> in the uſe of Means, and above Means, will prevail. There is a River, the Streams thereof will make glad the City of God, which is the Church of God throughout the whole World: For one fair Flood doth ſend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad ſuch pleaſant Streams apace to refreſh the City of our God, and to waſh his Holy Place. Is not the Mighty God in <hi>Sion?</hi> Go walk about, and go round about her, tell the Towers thereof, mark ye well her Bulwarks, conſider her Palaces, that ye may tell it to the Generation following; for God, who is moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong, is with her, and is known in her Palaces for a Refuge; She is Beautiful for Situation; the Joy of the whole Earth is <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> and the City of the great King. The Kings of the Earth in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Raign of our Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain;</hi> they will admire her Wiſdom, Power and Strength, her Honours, Riches and great Glory.</p>
            <p>Shall Deliverance be at hand, and the <hi>Church of England</hi> at a ſtand? Shall there be a Well of Water near <hi>Hagar,</hi> and ſhe weep and be in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs?
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:29672:60"/>Who hath heard ſuch a thing? who hath ſeen ſuch things? Shall the Earth be made to bring forth in one day? Or ſhall a Nation be born at once? For as ſoon as <hi>Sion</hi> travelled ſhe brought forth, before her pain came, ſhe was delivered of a Man-child. Shall the Lord, who is moſt Wiſe and moſt Strong, bring to the Birth, and not cauſe to bring forth; or cauſe to bring forth, and ſhut the Womb, ſaith thy God: No it will not be, for in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, <hi>His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of Great Britain,</hi> the God of Heaven has many Sons and Daughters that are grown up, and many to be brought up, and more to be brought forth in the uſe of the Means of Grace which he has appointed, and the <hi>Church of England</hi> has or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; but all the Children of the Moſt High that are brought up, and grown up, and to be brought forth; all is to be in oppoſition to the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and all the <hi>Workers of Evil;</hi> which will tend very much for the Glory of the Great and Mighty God, for the Credit of his holy Goſpel, for the great Honour and Renown of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> the great Joy and Triumph of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> the great Exaltation of <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain,</hi> and the great Peace and Proſperity of many Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>O that the Sons and the Daughters of Men were wiſe, for to make an Improvement of the Wiſdom and Power of the God of Heaven, which is better than Strength or Weapons of War, or Silver or Gold. As for the Wiſdom that is in the World,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:29672:61"/>among unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> bruitiſh <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> wicked and bloody <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and rebellious <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentors</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> it is fooliſhneſs, and doth many times end in madneſs; for where Envy, Strife, and Contention is, it brings forth too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sedition and Rebellion: But the Wiſdom that is from above, it is pure and peaceable, gentle and eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy and good fruits; without partiality, and without hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie: but where Pride, Envy, Strife, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is, there is Confuſion and every evil Work. Now a good man and a bad man will be known by their Fruits; for of Thorns men do not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Figs, nor of a Bramble-buſh gather they Grapes; but every Tree will be known by his own Fruit. A good man out of the good trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his heart, bringeth forth that which is good, that which is ſuitable and ſeaſonable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitable, comfortable, and advantageous to many Perſons and Families in a City, and in a Kingdom. But an evil man, who is a wicked man, out of the evil treaſure of his heart, bringeth forth that which is evil, to the great hurt and undoing of too many Perſons and Families in a City and in a Kingdom.</p>
            <p>It is commendable for the Sons of Men, the wiſeſt, the ſtrongeſt, the richeſt, and the moſt learnedſt among them, for to have always their heart to be Inditing of a good Matter, and their Tongue to be as the Pen of a ready Writer; that that ſo they may declare the thing that they have framed, for the great Honour and Renown of the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:29672:61"/>King our Royal Soveraign, <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain,</hi> and the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of his Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>How welcom ſhould, becauſe how Beautiful are, the Feet of him that bringeth good Tidings, that publiſheth Peace; that bringeth good Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of good, that ſaith unto <hi>Sion,</hi> the <hi>Church of England,</hi> Thy God Raigneth: Awake, awake, put on thy Strength, O <hi>Zion,</hi> put on thy Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Garments, O <hi>Church of England,</hi> ſhake thy ſelf from the Duſt, from the Reproaches that thy Enemies have caſt upon thee: Looſe thy ſelf from the bands of thy Neck, for thou ſhalt break forth on the right hand, and on the left, and thy Seed ſhall inherit the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and make the deſolate Cities to be inhabited; in Righteouſneſs ſhalt thou be eſtabliſhed; thou ſhalt be far from Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, for thou ſhalt not fear, and from terror, for it ſhall not come near thee, ſo as to hurt thee; the Sons of them that have afflicted thee, ſhall come bending unto thee, and all that deſpiſed thee, ſhall bow themſelves down at the Soles of thy Feet: And thy Enemies ſhall call thee, <hi>O Church of England,</hi> the City of the Lord, the <hi>Zion</hi> of the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Sing O Barren, thou that didſt not bear, break forth into Singing, and cry aloud thou that didſt not travel with Child; for more are the Children of the Deſolate, than the Children of the Married Wife, ſaith the Lord: Rejoyce ye with <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with the City of <hi>London,</hi> and be glad with her all ye that love her; Rejoyce for Joy with her, all ye that have mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:29672:62"/>for her; for the Lord will extend Peace to her like a River, and the Glory of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> like a ſlowing Stream; then ſhall ye ſuck and be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the Breaſts of her Conſolations, with the Means of Grace which God has appointed; for he will give unto thee, <hi>O Church of England;</hi> more and more Teachers after his own heart, which ſhall feed his people with Knowledge and Underſtanding; ſo that they ſhall milk out and be delighted with the abundance of thy Glory.</p>
            <p>And when you ſee this, you that are full of Fears and Doubts what will become of <hi>Zion?</hi> What will become of the <hi>Church of England?</hi> Your Hearts ſhall rejoyce, and your Bones ſhall flouriſh like an Herb; for the Hand of the Lord, the Power of the Lord, will be known towards his Servants, and his Indignation towards his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. The Nations that know not thy God, <hi>O Church of England,</hi> who is the true and the ever-living God, will be aſhamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, for all their Wiſdom, their Power and Strength; they ſhall lay their hand upon their Mouth, their Ears will be deaf, they ſhall lick the Duſt like a Serpent, they ſhall move out of their holes like Worms of the Earth, they ſhall be afraid of the Lord our God, and ſhall fear becauſe of thee, <hi>O Church of England:</hi> The Lord will be terrible unto thy Enemies, he will famiſh all the Gods of the Earth, that men may worſhip him, every one in his place, even all the Iſles of the Heathen: then the rejoycing City that dwelt careleſly, that ſaid in her Heart, I am, and there is none beſide
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:29672:62"/>me; how will ſhe become a Deſolation, a place for Beaſts to lie down in; every one that paſſeth by her ſhall hiſs and wag his head: for the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> who is the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> will become <hi>the Man of Sorrow:</hi> for the Lord will pour Contempt upon them that have poured Contempt upon his Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; as all unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> bruitiſh <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> wicked, bloody and deceitful <hi>Papists,</hi> proud <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentors,</hi> and rebellious <hi>Sectaries</hi> have done: But if that they will not learn in theſe days of the Goſpel to be humbled and reformed, they will be aſhamed and confounded. Fear not, O Land, but be glad and rejoyce, for the Lord, who is moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong, will do great things for thee, <hi>O England,</hi> for thee <hi>O London,</hi> above other Nations; for as thou haſt had great ſorrow and miſery, ſo thou wilt have great honour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity: The time is come in theſe days of the Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign, <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain,</hi> that for thy ſhame the Lord will give thee double Honour, and for Confuſion thou ſhalt greatly Rejoyce, everlaſting Joy ſhall be unto thee: Thou haſt drunken deep of the Cup of Gods Anger, but thy Enemies, they that hate thee, <hi>O Church of England,</hi> will drink the Dregs of it: Be glad then ye Children of <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and rejoyce in the Lord your God, for thou ſhalt be no more tearmed, <hi>Forſaken,</hi> for thou ſhalt forget the ſhame of thy Youth, and ſhalt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Reproach of thy Widow-hood any more, for thy Maker is thine Husband, the Lord
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:29672:63"/>of Hoſts is his Name. The Lord thy God in the midſt of thee, <hi>O Church of England,</hi> is mighty, he will ſave, he will rejoyce over thee with Joy, he will reſt in his Love, he will joy over thee with Singing; and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall ſee thy Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and all Kings thy Glory; for thou wilt be as a Crown of Glory in the hand of the Lord, and as a Royal Diadem in the hand of thy God: For as a young man marrieth a Virgin, ſo will thy Sons marry thee; and as the Bridegroom rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth over the Bride, ſo will thy God rejoyce over thee: Therefore ye that make mention of the Lord, keep not ſilence, and give him no reſt till he eſtabliſh, and till he make <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the City of <hi>London,</hi> a Praiſe in the Earth: Praiſe the Lord O <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> praiſe thy God O <hi>Zion,</hi> for he hath ſtrengthned the Bars of thy Gates, he hath bleſſed thy Children within thee; he maketh peace in thy Borders, and filleth thee with the ſineſt of the Wheat: He ſheweth his Word unto <hi>Jacob,</hi> his Statutes and his Judgments unto <hi>Iſrael;</hi> He hath not dealt ſo with other Nations, and as for his Judgments they have not known them: Praiſe ye the Lord that be wiſe, for it is good to ſing Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes unto our God; for it is pleaſant, and praiſe is comely: For great is our Lord, and of great Power, his Underſtanding is inſinite; he lifteth up the meek with much eaſe, when they be brought low, he caſteth the wicked down to the ground, when they be ſo proud as not to know him, and ſo high as not to fear him. O that all the Sons and the Daughters of Men in theſe days of the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:29672:63"/>Goſpel, and in the Reign of our Royal Soveraign <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain,</hi> would learn to be wiſe, and to know thoſe things that do concern their Everlaſting Peace, before they go hence and be ſeen no more; for Time flies, and Man daily dies: there is not an Hour in a Day, but many have their Breath taken away. All fleſh is graſs, and as the flower of the field, the graſs withereth, the flower fadeth, but the Word of thy God, <hi>O Church of England,</hi> ſhall ſtand for ever; Heaven and Earth will ſooner fail, than one Tittle of Gods Word. Where the Word of a King is, there is Power, but how much more where the Word of the everliving God is, when it is ſet on by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is a Spirit of Power, of Might, and of Majeſty? It is a meek and a quiet Spririt, an humble and a holy Spirit; and it is the higheſt, loftieſt, and moſt nobleſt Spirit; it is ſuch a Spirit that it will enable them that will be ruled by it, for to attain, retain, maintain, and proclaim that which is moſt noble, excellent, and advantageous, for the great Honour, Peace and Proſperity of a King and Kingdom: Let all People in all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions rejoyce in him that made them; let the Children of <hi>Zion</hi> be joyful in their King: The Lord ſhall Reign for ever, even thy God, <hi>O Church of England,</hi> unto all Generations; therefore praiſe him all ye Nations; let every thing that hath breath praiſe the Lord: Praiſe him for his mighty Acts; who can expreſs the Noble Acts of the Lord, they are ſo many and great? Not men or Angels: His wondrous Works in the Land of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:29672:64"/>
               <hi>Ham,</hi> and fearful things by the Red Sea: The Lord is good to all, and his tender mercies are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all his works; the Lord is great, and greatly to be Admired and Adored; he is clothed with Honour and Majeſty, who covereth himſelf with Light as with a Garment, who ſtretcheth out the Heavens like a Curtain, who layeth the Beams of his Chambers in the Waters, who maketh the Clouds his Chariot, who walketh upon the Wings of the Wind, who maketh his Angels Spirits, his Miniſters a flaming Fire; who laid the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Earth, that it ſhould not be removed for ever; the Lord of Hoſts is his Name.</p>
            <p>To be much in meditation of him will be ſweet to the Soul, and health to the Body: I will be glad and rejoyce in the Lord as long as I live, I will ſing praiſe to him while I have my being; for he hath redeemed my Life from Deſtruction, and hath Crowned me with Loving-kindneſs and tender Mercies; who ſatisfieth my Mouth with good things; ſo that my Youth has been renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the Eagles: Well may my Soul therefore bleſs the Lord, and all that is within me bleſs his holy Name: Bleſs the Lord O my Soul, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not any of his Benefits; who forgiveth all thine Iniquities, and healeth all thy Diſeaſes: The Glory of the Lord ſhall endure for ever; the Lord will rejoyce in his Works; the Lords Throne is in the Heavens, and his Kingdom ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth over all: Therefore bleſs the Lord ye his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels that excel in Strength, bleſs ye the Lord all ye his Hoſts, ye Miniſters of his that do his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:29672:64"/>bleſs the Lord all ye his Works in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Dominion.</p>
            <p>Is it not in vain for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for to pray, <hi>O God make ſpeed to ſave us; O Lord make haſt to help us;</hi> and do not mind and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard when and by whom he will do it by whom can do it when he will, ſo he will do it by whom he will; and not when and by whom Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned-men pleaſe; the meaner and weaker the Inſtrument is, whom Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God doth uſe, the greater is the Sin of them that do him ſlight, under-value, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe. Long may the <hi>Church of England</hi> look for Peace, and meet with Trouble; look for Health, and meet with Diſappointment; when ſhe is not careful to mind the Day of her Viſitation. Shall the Stork in the Heaven know her appointed time, and the Turtle, and the Crane, and the Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low obſerve the time of their coming? And ſhall not the Servants of the Lord underſtand his Mind, ſo as to endeavour to prevent his Judgments? Are they not counted wiſe-men that have the Law of the Lord with them? But are not ſuch wiſe-men many times diſmayed, aſhamed, and taken, when they do reject the Word of the Lord, and rely upon the Traditions and Inventions of Mens ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and framing, which are neither agreeable nor ſuitable to the Word of God, which is the Word of Life and of Power? What wiſdom is in ſuch men then, that wiſdom which will deceive them? Who is ſo blind as they that ſhould ſee moſt, and deaf as they that ſhould hear beſt? Is there
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:29672:65"/>no Balm in <hi>Gilead,</hi> is there no Phyſician there? Doubtleſs there is: Is not the Lord, the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> in whom is Everlaſting Strength in <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> Is not her King in her, and for her, and with her? Why then is not the health of the Daughter of Gods people recovered? Is there not any that ſtirs up himſelf to take hold of the true and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living God, as they ought and ſhould do; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath the Lord, who is full of Wiſdom, Power, and Strength, hid his Face from us: And by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our many great and grievous Sins, we have all been very much afflicted and conſumed? But where is the man that lays it ſo to heart, as to ſtand up in the Gap, to make up the Hedge, ſo as to turn away Gods Wrath, that for a long time has burned like Fire againſt <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> Who can ſtand before the Lord, who is moſt great, and moſt good, when once he is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry; doth not the Mountains quake at him, and the Hills melt? And is not the Earth burnt at his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, yea the World, and all that dwell therein, when he pleaſeth? Therefore the Wicked and all the Workers of Iniquity, the Seed of Evil-doers, the Children of Diſobedience, the Enemies of the Goſpel, and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, confounded, and at laſt deſtroyed, if that they do not in time humble themſelves under the hands of the Great and Mighty God, who is Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor and Commander of Heaven, the Earth, and the Sea, and all things that in them be. The Righteous ſhall rejoyce and be glad, but the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in <hi>Zion,</hi> in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> will be
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:29672:65"/>afraid: Fearfulneſs hath ſurprized the Hypocrites already: Who among the Sons of Men in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that can dwell with Devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire? Who among them can dwell with Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Burnings? He that walketh Righteouſly, and worketh Righteouſneſs; that ſpeaketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly; he that deſpiſeth the Gain of Oppreſſion, that ſlacketh his hands from holding of Bribes; that ſtoppeth his Ears from hearing of Blood, and ſhutteth his Eyes from ſeeing of Evil; he ſhall dwell on high, his place of Defence ſhall be the Munitions of Rocks; in time of Famine he will be fed; Bread ſhall be given him, his Waters ſhall be ſure, he ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty; he will behold the Land that is very far off: But what will become of them that ſerve graven Images, and boaſt themſelves of Idols? they will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed and confounded in theſe Days of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, if that they do not loth and forſake them. In theſe Days of the Goſpel, the Lord who is moſt great, and moſt good, moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong, is very angry, and has been for a long time with this Generation; but moſt of all with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel throughout the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for not minding and regarding who hath believed their Report, and to whom the Arm of the Lord is revealed; for his Arm is very long, and very ſtrong; and that his Enemies the Workers of Iniquity will know in theſe Days of the Goſpel, to their great ſhame and overthrow. Ought not the Miniſters of the Goſpel to mind what they ſow in weakneſs, in whom the Great
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:29672:66"/>and the Mighty God doth raiſe in Power, or elſe they do but undervalue their own Labours, and encourage their Adverſaries, who labour to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine and overthrow the <hi>Proteſtant Religion, His Majeſty of Great Britain,</hi> and the <hi>Church of England.</hi> What have the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel to mind? Who ought they to mind more than that man whom the Lord of Hoſts has made ſtrong for himſelf and his Anointed; when that too many have made themſelves ſtrong in Parts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and our Royal Soveraign, <hi>His Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſty of Great Britain?</hi> But what will they get but ſhame and confuſion, for they will be brought down and that with a witneſs. Though it is not in the power of the Miniſters of the Goſpel to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſo Renowned a Grace, as precious Faith where it is not; yet ought it to be their great Care to countenance, incourage, and take notice of that perſon in whom it is wrought; becauſe it is ſuch a ſpark, that it will in time break forth into a ſlame, for the Glory of Gods great Name, and to put the Enemies of the Goſpel to ſhame: It is high and honourable Work, that the God of Heaven has ſtirr'd me up for to make known his Mind, for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of Mankind. And I have endeavoured to deny my ſelf, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my ſelf, and to lay out my ſelf, in ſo noble a Deſign; I have ventur'd my Life, endangered my Liberty, and have expoſed my ſelf to many Loſſes, Croſſes, and Reproaches, to be blam'd, ſham'd, and condemn'd by many men: But I had rather be condemn'd for doing well, though I do
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:29672:66"/>it not ſo well as I ſhould do, by the Sons of Men, than to be condemn'd by the God of Heaven, for not making known his Mind, as well as I can do: The Lord is merciful, and will paſs by many Weakneſſes and Infirmities of his Children; but he is juſt and righteous, and will puniſh ſeverely them that be rebellious and diſobedient: They that know their Lords will and do it not, will have ſtripes enough; for though the Lord be ſlow to anger, yet is he great in Power: They that do ſlight and under-value me, it is not ſo much me, as they do the Wiſdom and the Power of the Almighty, who works with me, and in me, and for me, for the Glory of his great Name, for the Credit of his holy Goſpel, for the great Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Renown of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> for the great Exaltation of <hi>His Majeſty of Great Britain,</hi> above all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Emperors in the World; which will bring great Joy and Triumph to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and great Peace and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to many Kingdoms; which will be brought about in theſe days of the Goſpel, in ſpight of the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Divel,</hi> and all the Workers of Evil. It is the Power of Faith, which is the Power of God, that doth ſet a-work the Powers of the Soul, and the Powers of the Soul ſet a-work by the Powers of Heaven, will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to prepare high and honourable Work, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, proſitable and delightſom Work, victorious, glorious, and crowning Work, to be managed by the Powers of the World, for the Glory of the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:29672:67"/>moſt High, and the great Honour and Renown of <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Majeſty: That all Strife, Contention and Wars throughout the whole World may ceaſe; that ſo among all People in all Nations, there may be a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace.</p>
            <p>The Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt not be Countenanced, Encouraged, or Tolerated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of Men, in any Nation, City, Town, or Corporation, under the Canopy of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe it is a Religion full of Deceit, and throughout the whole World the greateſt Cheat: It is a Religion that is an Idle Fowl, that doth at once pick the Purſe, and damn the Soul: It is a Religion managed with all the Crafts of the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil;</hi> therefore it is a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion full of Pride, Vain glory, Hypocriſie, and Treachery: It is a wicked Religion, becauſe it makes them that Conform to it, to be ſeven-ſold more the Children of the Devil than they were by Nature. All the Sons and the Daughters of Men are bad by Nature, but the Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> makes Men worſe by Practice: But, <hi>God ſo loved the World,</hi> that he has ſent the Goſpel of his Son, which is taught in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that Men might be turned from a ſtate of Nature, into a ſtate of Grace; and from the power of Sin and Satan, into the <hi>Glorious Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of his Children;</hi> which is to injoy Power againſt Sin, and Victory over the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and all the <hi>Workers of Evil.</hi> But the Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> makes her
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:29672:67"/>Children Servants to Sin, Slaves to the World and the Devil, and Enemies to their own Souls; and ſo being hardned in Sin by Cuſtom and Practice, they are not afraid nor aſhamed to Combine and Deſign from time to time, to undermine and overthrow the <hi>Proteſtant Religion, His Majesty of Great Britain,</hi> and the <hi>Church of England:</hi> But for ever bleſſed and praiſed be the God of Heaven, who to Admiration, from time to time has watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over this Nation, that it has not by unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, bloody, and deceitful Men, been brought to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; but no thanks be to them that have made a Separation, for they have done what they can to put a Sword into our Enemies hand: By their Pride and Contention, Sedition, and Rebellion, many have turned <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts;</hi> ſo that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has been ſtrengthned and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged from our Selves. Ever ſince the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has made Shipwrack of Faith and of a good Conſcience, and has preferred their Traditions, Inventions, and lying Wonders, above Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, which is the Rule of Faith and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; their Religion has been an abominable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto Chriſt and his Goſpel: They do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt, but they do deny him, becauſe they will not be ruled by his Word, nor have him rule in them by his Spirit: They do mock Chriſt in their Sacraments, and perſecute him in his Members; ſo that the Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a bloody Religion, upheld by Tyranny and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: The Blood that the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> has cauſed to be ſhed in the World from time to time,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:29672:68"/>by Wars, Treachery, and Cruelty; is more than there be men in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> And yet the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Mother of <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots,</hi> that Scarlet Whore, is not ſatisfied; but the Righteous God to whom Vengeance doth belong, though he be ſlow to Anger, yet is he great in Power; therefore he will give her Blood to Drink, becauſe ſhe is worthy: The Day of thy Calamity, <hi>O Church of Rome,</hi> is at hand; that ſo many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be freed from Slavery, and throughout the whole World there may be great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity. For thy Pride and Vain-glory, thy Formality, Hypocriſie, and Treachery, the Miſery that will come upon thee, maketh haſt: Therefore Cry and Howl you Inhabitants of <hi>Rome,</hi> for <hi>Antichriſt</hi> muſt come down; and all thoſe that will uphold his Crown: to that end the Lord of Hoſts, who is Strong and Mighty in Battel, who has all Power in his own hand, and the whole Creation at command, has ſtirr'd me up to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage with him, to ſtir up all the Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the world that will own him, to bring down his Implacable Enemies that be againſt him, as the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>French King,</hi> and the <hi>King of Spain,</hi> becauſe they be Enemies to his Goſpel, and his Children, who are as dear unto him as the Apple of his Eye, becauſe they be his purchaſed, ranſomed, and redeemed Ones, they be his juſtified, ſanctified, choſen and beloved Ones; they be his choice Jewels, and his great Treaſure: As for the Workers of Iniquity, the Seed of Evil Doers, the Children of Diſobedience,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:29672:68"/>the Enemies of his Goſpel; who be unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> bruitiſh <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> wicked and bloody <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> and rebellious <hi>Diſſentors</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> they be but Lumber and Cumber in the world, till they do Conform and Reform to the Lord of Life, who is the King of Glory, and the Prince of Peace; who knows when, how, and by whom he pleaſe, with much eaſe, to bring great Peace and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to a Nation, as to a Perſon; happy be they that live to him, and live for him; they will live for ever with him; they will be in his Favour, in whoſe Preſence is Fulneſs of Joy, and at whoſe Right Hand are Pleaſures for ever-more. It is a great Priviledge to be in the Favour of an Earthly Prince; but it is the higheſt Honour, and the greateſt Safety to be in the Favour of the God of Heaven, who is the Lord of Life and the King of Glory.</p>
            <p>A man may want Money ſometimes to help himſelf, when he may be rich and ſtrong in Faith to help others. A man may want Money to Trade with men, when he may be rich and ſtrong in Faith, to engage with the God of Heaven, for the Glory of his great Name, to have his Enemies brought to ſhame, and <hi>His Majeſly of Great. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and the <hi>Church of England,</hi> throughout the whole world, to great Honour, Renown, and Fame: True Faith, which is more precious than Gold, will make a man ſeeming poor, to make others really rich; and it will inable a man to make himſelf in the world of no Reputation, to bring others to great Honour and Exaltation: Let all
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:29672:69"/>that want ſo rich a Jewel as precious Faith, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to get it from the Lord of Life, in the uſe of thoſe means that he has appointed, and the <hi>Church of England</hi> has ordained; and they that have it, let them labour to prove it, and improve it, becauſe it will innoble the Mind, and inable the Mind to frame ſome noble Deſign, and to bring it about in due time, for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Mankind. It has been want of Faith and Love to God, our Brethren, and Enemies, that has cauſed ſo much Strife and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, Sedition, and Rebellion; which has brought great Diſorder and Confuſion from time to time among Mankind: But the God of Wiſdom and Power knows when and how for to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of Men, in many Nations, Order out of Confuſion, Light out of Darkneſs, Good out of Evil, Peace out of Trouble in the worſt of Times; and by the weakeſt of Means: that Strife, Contentions, and Wars throughout the whole Earth may ceaſe: All People in all Nations muſt ſtrive to live in Love and Peace, becauſe God is Love, who is the Creator of all Men, and the Preſerver of them.</p>
            <p>That this may be done, and well done, the Goſpel, that bringeth Glad-tydings of Salvation, muſt Run and be Glorified, where it is not, and muſt flouriſh where it is; that ſo they that do not know the true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent, may labour to know him; and they that know him, let them labour to love him; and they that love him, let them labour to keep his
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:29672:69"/>Commandments, becauſe they be not grievous, but moſt pleaſant, profitable, and comfortable: But the Traditions of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are burdenſom, unprofitable, and uncomfortable; they do deprive Kings of their Priviledges: And that is the greateſt Freedom, which is the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Mind, and the greateſt Liberty which is the Liberty of the Will, and the greateſt Power which is over Sin, the World, and the Devil. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is too cruel to her Children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe will not let them injoy the Jewels more worth than three Kingdoms: And that is a ſound Heart which is the life of the Fleſh; a wholſom Tongue which is a Tree of Life, and righteous Lips which are the Delight of Kings; but to lye, ſlatter, and diſſemble, is the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Religion. The Lips of Truth will be eſtabliſht for ever, but a lying Tongue is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Times may be ſo bad, and ſo ſad, that many may be brought into ſuch great ſtraights, that they cannot tell how to live well by their Eſtates, or their Trades, by their Houſes or Lands, or Offices, or great Places; but in the worſt of Times that can come, the Juſt ſhall live by his Faith, becauſe it is more precious than Gold: In time of Famine he will be fed, in time of Plague he will be hid, in time of War he will not fly, in time of Fire he is provided for all Eternity; when the Heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, and the Earth, and all the Works that are therein ſhall be burnt up, then the Juſt and Righteous have
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:29672:70"/>an Inheritance incorruptible and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in Heaven for them.</p>
            <p>Faith that works by Love, will inable the Sons and the Daughters of Men to bear much, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer much, to want much, and to enjoy much, and to do much good in their Generation; for the great Honour of God, the King, and Nation; they that can love the God of Heaven for himſelf, will ſerve him for his Kingdom; and they will know that the God of Heaven loves them, but not for what they have done and ſuffered, but he loves them for his Son, and for what he has done and ſuffered: They that do love God for Chriſt, and the Lord Chriſt as God and Man in one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, will find that the Father and the Son will manifeſt themſelves unto them; and by their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will revive, refreſh, counſel, comfort, and ſtrengthen them in every State and Condition, under every Tryal, Trouble, and Affliction, that the Sons and the Daughters of Men are expoſed unto in the Wilderneſs of this World. The God of Heaven, who is moſt Great and moſt Good, moſt wiſe, and moſt ſtrong, is Love, and he that dwelleth in Love, dweleth in God; and God in him; which will enable a man to bring about great and wonderful things, for the great Honour and Exaltation of a Kings Perſon, and the great Peace and Proſperity of many Nations.</p>
            <p>Man's loving of God, who is moſt good, is a Fruit of Gods loving of him, though he be very bad, but not the Cauſe: Gods Love to Man is
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:29672:70"/>free, he don't deſerve it, neither can any of the Sons and Daughters of Men merit it by all their Works and Duties: Mans love to God is a Duty, the God of Heaven doth require it, becauſe that he is moſt worthy of it, to be beloved above all, and more than all: They that love the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven moſt, will ſerve and honour him beſt; and they that honour him, he will them; to ſome he doth it in this World, with Honours, Riches, and a long Life; but to all that be faithful and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in good Works, ſuch works that be pleaſing to him, and profitable to others; he will honour in his own Kingdom with Glory, Immortality, and the Crown of Liſe.</p>
            <p>O Great is the Power of Faith, which is the Power of the God of Heaven, which doth inable a weak and an unlikely man for to prepare high and honourable Work, pleaſant, profitable, and delightſome Work, Victorious, Glorious, and Crowning Work; to be managed by many Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men, for the Glory of the Great and Mighty God, for the Credit of his Holy Goſpel, for the great Honour and Renown of the Proteſtant Religion, for the great Honour and Exaltation of our Royal Soveraign his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> above all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Emperors in the World: ſo that we ſhall become the wonder of the World, and a wonder to our ſelves; the Deſire and the Delight of Nations, the Joy of the whole Earth, and the City of the great King, for Unity, Peace and Concord, for Piety
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:29672:71"/>and Vertue, for Wiſdom, Power, and Strength; and for Honours, Riches, and great Glory; which will be brought about in theſe days of the Goſpel, but not by the Power of the Sword made by Men, but by the Power of Faith, which is the Wiſdom and Power of the God of Heaven: Therefore Glory be to God moſt high, great Joy, Peace, Proſperity, and good will towards Men on Earth, Glory and great Glory from all Men and Angels; to the moſt High: Great Honour and Renown, great Joy, Peace and Proſperity, is for <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Majeſty: Therefore with Angels and Archangels, and all the Company of Heaven, the glorious Company of the Apoſtles, the goodly Fellow-ſhip of the Prophets, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Army of Martyrs, the Holy Church of Chriſt throughout the whole World; let us all laud and magnifie, praiſe and glorifie the God of Heaven, the Father of an infinite Majeſty, for his unſpeakable Love and innumerable Mercies, from time to time beſtowed on Mankind, for the ſake of his beloved Son, our bleſſed Lord and only Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who ever liveth and ever loveth, and will take great Delight and Pleaſure to reward them that be Wiſe, Faithful, Valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and Couragious to the end: But they that draw back unto Perdition, and unto the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Tradition; his Soul will take no pleaſure in them: but they that honour him he will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them, not onely before Mortal Men, but before his Father and Holy Angels in the higheſt Heavens. Therefore Glory and great Glory be to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:29672:71"/>him; and great Honour and Renown to <hi>England's</hi> Royal King, our Gracious Soveraign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, by his Grace and Favour, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> above all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes and Emperors in the World; that ſo all Strife, Contention and Wars throughout the whole World may ceaſe; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all People in all Nations there may be a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>WHat the God of Heaven has promiſed in time for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Mankind, it will be brought about in due time; for all his Promiſes are true and faithful, every one more precious than Gold, or the Gold of <hi>Ophir:</hi> The Crown of Glory is in a promiſe; them that be faithful to the Death will he give the Crown of Life. The God of Heaven promiſed to ſend his Son, and in the fulneſs of time he did come, who is, and was, and ever will be, the chiefeſt of Ten thouſands in the higheſt degree; and in theſe days of the Goſpel the Lord will give unto him the Heathen for his Inheritance, and the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt parts of the Earth for his Porfeſſion; for the Glory of his great Name; to have his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies brought to ſhame, and many Kings and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:29672:72"/>Kingdoms, to great Honour, Renown, and Fame. To him that believes and knows he believes, all things is poſſible to be done that is lawful, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, and moſt honourable under the Sun. By what Divine Wiſdom and Power has inabled me for to make known in time for the great Honour and Exaltation of his Majeſties Royal Perſon, and the great Joy, Peace, and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of many Nations; the Reader that is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious, may learn to be good, and to know when and how for to do much good in his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; for the great Honour of God, the King, and Nation; and that in the worſt of times and before the beſt of Men; and that without making of many words, or having the voice much heard. Theſe days of the Goſpel are times that will try the Wiſdom and the Skill, the Valour and the Courage of many Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men, what they can do, and what they will do, for to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that noble Deſign, that Divine Wiſdom and Power has inabled me to make known in time, for the Glory of his great Name, for the Credit of his Holy Goſpel, for the great Honour and Renown of the Proteſtant Religion, for the great Joy and Triumph of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> which will bring great Peace and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity to many Kingdoms; which is to be brought about in theſe days of the Goſpel, for the Glory of the moſt High, and for the great Honour and Exaltation of <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; that ſo many Nations may be freed from
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:29672:72"/>Slavery, and throughout the whole World there may be great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity. The great and the mighty God, who is moſt Wiſe and moſt Strong, doth what whatſoever will, in the Heavens above and in the Farth beneath; and that when he pleaſe and with whom he pleaſe: and that many great and mighty Kings have found.</p>
            <p>I ſhall name but two or three, and that is King <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> King <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> and that great King <hi>Nebuchad-nezzar,</hi> who in the midſt of his Glory, and in his Royal Palace of <hi>Babel,</hi> that he built for the Houſe of the Kingdom, who was boaſting of his Power, and the great Honour of his Majeſty; while the word was in the Kings Mouth, a Voice came down from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>O King Nebuchad-nezzar;</hi> to him it was ſpoken that his Kingdom was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from him, and that he ſhould be driven from Men, and that his Dwelling ſhould be with the Beaſts of the Field, and that he ſhould eat Graſs as the Oxen; and ſeven times ſhould paſs over him, until he did know that the moſt High beareth Rule over the Kingdoms of Men, and giveth them unto whomſoever he will; the very ſame hour was this thing fulfilled upon <hi>Nebuchad-nezzar,</hi> and he was driven from Men, and did eat Graſs as the Oxen, and his Body was wet with the Dew of Heaven, till his Hairs were grown as Eagles Feathers, and his Nails like Birds Claws: and when the term of Seven years was accompliſhed, which from the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:29672:73"/>God of Heaven was prefixed; at the end of thoſe days did <hi>Nebuchad-nezzar</hi> lift up his Eyes unto Heaven, and his Underſtanding was reſtored unto him: Then did he give thanksunto the moſt High, and praiſed and honoured him that liveth for ever, whoſe Dominion is an Everlaſting Dominion and his Kingdom is from Generation to Generation; and before him all the Inhabitants of the Earth are reputed as nothing: and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will he worketh in the Army of Heaven, and among the Inhabitants of the Earth; and none can ſtay his Hand, nor ſay unto him, <hi>What doſt thou?</hi> Therefore he is to be feared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Gods, becauſe that he is a Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>working God, a Great and a Glorious God; who can work Wonders in a Man and with a Man, either for or againſt a City or a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; for his Works are all Truth, and his Ways Judgments; and thoſe that walk in Pride he is able to abaſe: but the Meek, Humble, and the Lowly, doth he delight in, among the Sons of Men, and will bring them in due time to great Honour and Glory in his Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>I am a Friend and a Lover of all them that are not Enemies unto themſelves, as all Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Jews, Bruitiſh Atheiſts, Wicked and Bloody Papiſts, and Robellious Diſſentors and Sectaries are, and that will not Conform Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Lord of Life, who is the King of Glory, and the Prince of Peace, whoſe Service is perfect Freedom, and his Work and Reward
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:29672:73"/>is moſt Proſitable, moſt Honourable, moſt Comfortable, moſt Satisfying, Laſting, and Everlaſting.</p>
            <p>What Divine Wiſdom and Power has inabled me to make known in time for <hi>Englands</hi> Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Reformation, great Joy, Peace, and Conſolation, and for her great Honour and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, it is by <hi>John Varney,</hi> a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> a City, that has been a City of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown, and will come to greater Honour, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown and Fame, in his Majeſties Royal Reign, than any City under the Heaven, is or has been ſince <hi>England</hi> has injoyed a King.</p>
         </div>
         <closer>
            <dateline>
               <date>
                  <hi>September</hi> 27th. 1679.</date>
            </dateline>
         </closer>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:29672:74"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 41 line 16, read <hi>in this World;</hi> p. 46 l. 28, for <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial men</hi> r. <hi>mortal men;</hi> p. 95 l. 11, f. <hi>make known,</hi> r. <hi>made known;</hi> p. 103 l. 24, f. <hi>the Luſt of Evil,</hi> r. <hi>the Hurt of Evil;</hi> p. 104 l. 17, f. <hi>And that Men,</hi> r. <hi>O that Men;</hi> p. 105 l. 8, f. <hi>Right</hi> r. <hi>Height;</hi> p. 142 l. 39, f. <hi>and that will not Conform Reform,</hi> r. <hi>that will not Conform and Reform.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
